There's an old joke. Two elderly women
are at a Catskill Mountain resort.
One of 'em says, "The food
at this place is really terrible."
The other one says,
"Yeah, I know. And such small portions."
That's essentially
how I feel about life.
Full of loneliness and misery
and suffering and unhappiness.
And it's all over much too quickly.
The other important joke for me is one
that's usually attributed to Groucho Marx.
I think it appears originally in Freud's
Wit and its Relation to the Unconscious.
It goes like this - I'm paraphrasing.
I would never wanna belong to any club...
...that would have
someone like me for a member.
That's the key joke of my adult life
in terms of my relationships with women.
Lately the strangest things
have been going through my mind.
Cos I turned 40, and I guess
I'm going through a life crisis.
I'm not worried about ageing.
Although I'm balding slightly on top.
That's about the worst
you can say about me.
I think I'm gonna get better as I get older.
I think I'm gonna be
the balding virile type...
...as opposed to, say,
the distinguished grey, for instance.
Unless I'm one of those guys with
saliva dribbling out of his mouth...
...who wanders into a cafeteria
with a shopping bag...
...screaming about socialism.
Annie and I broke up.
And I still can't get my mind around that.
I keep sifting the pieces of
the relationship through my mind...
...examining my life, and trying to
figure out - where did the screwup come?
A year ago we were... in love, you know.
And... It's funny... I'm not a morose type.
I'm not a depressive character.
I... I, uh... You know...
I was a reasonably happy kid, I guess.
I was brought up in Brooklyn
during World War ll.
He's been depressed.
All of a sudden he can't do anything.
- Why are you depressed, Alvy?
- Tell Dr Flicker.
It's something he read.
Something he read, uh?
- The universe is expanding.
- The universe is expanding?
The universe is everything. If it's
expanding, someday it will break apart...
...and that will be the end of everything.
What is that your business?
He stopped doing his homework.
- What's the point?
- What has the universe got to do with it?
You're here in Brooklyn!
Brooklyn is not expanding!
It won't be expanding
for billions of years yet, Alvy.
And we've gotta try and enjoy ourselves
while we're here, uh?
Uh? Uh? (laughs)
My analyst says I exaggerate
my childhood memories.
But I was brought up
under the roller coaster...
...in the Coney Island section of Brooklyn.
Maybe that accounts for my personality,
which is a little nervous.
I have a hyperactive imagination.
My mind tends to jump around a little.
I have some trouble
between fantasy and reality.
My father ran the bumper car concession.
There he is.
And there I am.
I used to get my aggression out
through those cars all the time.
I remember the staff at our public school.
We had a saying:
"Those who can't do, teach...
...and those who can't teach, teach gym."
And those who couldn't do anything,
I think, were assigned to our school.
I always thought
my schoolmates were idiots.
Melvyn Greenglass. His fat little face.
And Henrietta Farrell.
Just Miss Perfect all the time.
And Ivan Ackerman.
Always the wrong answer. Always.
Seven and three is nine.
Even then, I knew they were just jerks.
In 1942 I had already discovered women.
Ugh! He kissed me!
He kissed me! Ugh!
That's the second time this month!
Step up here! Step up here!
- What did I do?
- You should be ashamed of yourself.
Why? I was just expressing
a healthy sexual curiosity.
Six-year-old boys
don't have girls on their minds.
I did.
For God's sakes, Alvy!
Even Freud speaks of a latency period.
Well, I never had a latency period.
I can't help it.
Why couldn't you have been more like
Donald? Now there was a model boy.
Tell the folks where you are today.
I run a profitable dress company.
Sometimes I wonder
where my classmates are today.
I'm president of
the Pinkus Plumbing Company.
I sell tallises.
I used to be a heroin addict.
Now I'm a methadone addict.
I'm into leather.
I lost track of most of my schoolmates,
but I wound up a comedian.
They did not take me in the army.
I was... Interestingly enough... I was 4-P.
In the event of war, I'm a hostage.
(laughter)
You always only saw the worst in people.
You never could get along
with anyone in school.
You were always out of step
with the world.
Even when you got famous,
you still distrusted the world.
(Alvy) I distinctly heard it.
He muttered under his breath, "Jew."
(Rob) You're crazy.
(Alvy) We were walking off
the tennis court. Him and me and his wife.
He looked at her and they both looked at
me. And under his breath he said, "Jew."
Alvy, you're a total paranoid.
(Alvy) I pick up on those kinda things.
I was having lunch with some guys from
NBC. So I said, "Did you eat yet or what?"
And Tom Christie said, "No. D'you?"
Not "Did you". "D'you eat?" "D'you?"
Not "Did you eat?" but "D'you eat?"
"Jew?" You get it? "Jew eat?"
- Max...
- Stop calling me Max.
Why, Max? It's a good name for you.
Max, you see conspiracies in everything.
(Alvy) I was in a record store. There's
this big, tall, blond, crew-cutted guy...
...looking at me in a funny way and saying,
"We have a sale this week on Wagner."
Wagner, Max. Wagner. I know what he's
really trying to tell me, very significantly.
Right, Max.
California, Max.
- Get the hell out of this crazy city.
- Forget it.
We move to sunny LA.
All of show business is there.
No. I don't wanna live in a city
where the only cultural advantage...
...is that you can make
a right turn on a red light.
Forget it.
Aren't you late for meeting Annie?
I'm meeting her at the Beekman.
I have a few minutes.
Are you on television?
No.
Yeah. Once in a while. Occasionally.
- What's your name?
- You wouldn't know it. It doesn't matter.
You were on the... uh...
The Johnny Carson, right?
Once in a while, you know.
What's your name?
I'm... I'm Robert Redford.
Come on!
Alvy Singer. It was nice...
Thanks very much for everything.
Hey!
(man) What?
This is Alvy Singer!
Fellas, you know...
This guy's on television.
Alvy Singer? Am I right?
- Give me a break.
- This guy's on television.
I need a large polo mallet.
- Who's on television?
- On The Johnny Carson Show.
Is this a meeting of the Teamsters?
- What programme?
- Can I have your autograph?
- You don't want my autograph.
- No, I do. It's for my girlfriend.
Make it out to Ralph.
- Your girlfriend's name is Ralph?
- It's for my brudder.
- Alvy Singer!
- You're really Alvy Singer, the TV star?
Alvy Singer over here!
It's all right, fellas.
Jesus! What did you do?
Come by way of the Panama Canal?
- I'm in a bad mood.
- I'm here with the cast of The Godfather.
- You have to learn to deal with it.
- I'm dealing with guys named Cheech!
Please. I have a headache, all right?
You are in a bad mood.
You must be getting your period.
Every time anything out of the ordinary
happens, you think I'm getting my period!
A little louder. I think
one of them may have missed it.
- Has the picture started?
- It started two minutes ago.
That's it. Forget it. I can't go in.
- Two minutes, Alvy.
- I can't do it. We've blown it already.
I can't go in in the middle.
We'll only miss the titles.
They're in Swedish.
- You wanna get coffee for two hours?
- Two hours? No. I'm going in.
- Go ahead. Goodbye.
- While we're talking, we could be inside.
Can we not stand here and argue
in front of everybody? I get embarrassed.
All right. So what do you wanna do?
I don't know now.
You wanna go to another movie?
Let's go see The Sorrow and the Pity.
Come on. I'm not in the mood to see
a four-hour documentary on Nazis.
Well, I'm sorry. I've gotta see a picture
exactly from the start to the finish.
Cos... Cos I'm anal.
That's a polite word for what you are.
We saw the Fellini film last Tuesday.
It is not one of his best.
It lacks a cohesive structure.
You get the feeling that he's not
absolutely sure what it is he wants to say.
I've always felt he was essentially
a technical filmmaker.
Granted, La Strada was a great film.
Great in its use of negative imagery.
I can't stand this guy.
I'm gonna have a stroke.
Well, stop listening to him.
He's screaming his opinions in my ear.
Like all that Juliet of the Spirits
or Satyricon.
I found it incredibly... indulgent.
He really is. He's one of
the most indulgent filmmakers.
The key word here is indulgent.
Without getting...
- What are you depressed about?
- I missed my therapy. I overslept.
- How can you possibly oversleep?
- The alarm clock.
Do you know
what a hostile gesture that is to me?
I know.
Because of our sexual problem, right?
Everybody at The New Yorker
has to know our rate of intercourse?
It's like Samuel Beckett.
I admire the technique,
but it doesn't hit me on a gut level.
- I'd like to hit this guy on a gut level.
- Stop it, Alvy!
He's spitting on my neck.
He's spitting on my neck when he talks.
You know, you're so egocentric
that if I miss my therapy...
...you can only think of it
in terms of how it affects you.
Weltanschauung is what it is.
Probably on their first date.
Probably met by answering an ad
in the New York Review of Books.
"Thirtyish academic
wishes to meet woman...
...who's interested in Mozart,
James Joyce and sodomy."
Our sexual problem? I'm comparatively
normal for a guy raised in Brooklyn.
OK. I'm very sorry. My sexual problem.
OK? My sexual problem. Huh?
I never read that. That was a Henry James
novel? Sequel of The Turn of the Screw?
It's the influence of television.
Now, Marshall McLuhan deals with it
in terms of it being a high...
...high intensity.
You understand? A hot medium...
What I wouldn't give for a large sock
with horse manure in it.
What do you do when you get stuck in
a movie line with a guy like this behind?
Why can't I give my opinion?
It's a free country.
Do you have to give it so loud? Aren't
you ashamed to pontificate like that?
The funny part is, you don't know
anything about Marshall McLuhan.
Really? I happen to teach a class
at Columbia called TV, Media and Culture.
So I think my insights into Mr McLuhan
have a great deal of validity.
Oh, do you? That's funny, because
I happen to have Mr McLuhan right here.
Just let me... Come over here a second.
I heard what you were saying.
You know nothing of my work.
You mean my whole fallacy is wrong.
How you ever got to teach a course
in anything is totally amazing.
Boy, if life were only like this!
June 14th, 1940.
The German army occupies Paris.
All over the country, people are desperate
for every available scrap of news.
(Alvy) Those guys in the French
Resistance were really brave.
To have to listen to
Maurice Chevalier sing so much.
Sometimes I ask myself
how I'd stand up under torture.
The Gestapo would take away
your Bloomingdale's charge card...
...and you'd tell 'em everything.
That movie makes me feel guilty.
Yeah, cos it's supposed to.
ANY...
What? What... What's the matter?
I don't... I don't know.
It's not natural. We're sleeping in a bed
together. You know, it's been a long time.
Well, it's just that I gotta sing tomorrow
night, so I have to rest my voice.
There's always an excuse.
You used to think I was very sexy.
When we first started going out,
we had sex constantly.
We're probably
in the Guinness Book of World Records.
Alvy, it'll pass.
I'm going through a phase. That's all.
You've been married before.
You know how things can get.
You were very hot for Allison at first.
(audience laughter)
You're on right after Chris Brown,
which looks about 20 minutes.
Excuse me. When do I go on?
Who are you?
Alvy Singer.
I'm a comedian.
Oh, comedian. Yeah.
Oh. You're on next.
What do you mean, next? I'm...
You're on right after this act.
No, it can't be. Because he's a comic.
Yes.
- You're putting on two comics in a row?
- Why not?
No, I'm sorry. I don't wanna go on
after another comedian.
It's OK.
No. Because they're laughing.
So I'd... rather not.
Will you relax? They're gonna love you.
I'd prefer not to. Look.
They're laughing at him.
They're gonna laugh at him
then I gotta go out.
I gotta get laughs too.
How much can they laugh?
- They're laughed out.
- Do you feel all right?
Jesus!
What's your name?
Allison.
Yeah?
Allison what?
Portchnik.
Portchnik?
- That's nice.
- Thank you.
Allison Portchnik! (whistles)
So, what are you telling me? You work
for Stevenson all the time or what?
No,no,no.
I'm in the midst of doing my thesis.
On what?
Political Commitment
in 20th-Century Literature.
You're like... New York, Jewish,
left-wing, liberal, intellectual...
...Central Park West, Brandeis University,
socialist summer camps?
The father with the Ben Shahn drawings?
The really strike-oriented...
Stop me before I make
a complete imbecile of myself.
No. That was wonderful. I love
being reduced to a cultural stereotype.
Right. I'm a bigot. But for the Left.
(laughter and applause)
I have to go out there.
Say something encouraging. Quickly.
I think you're cute.
- Do you?
- Mm-hm.
Go ahead.
(coughs)
I don't know why they would have me
at this kind of rally cos...
...I'm not essentially
a political comedian at all.
I interestingly had, um... dated a woman...
...in the Eisenhower administration briefly.
And it was ironic to me cos, um...
Cos I was trying to do to her...
...what Eisenhower has been doing
to the country for the last eight years.
(laughter and applause)
I'm sorry. I can't go through with this.
I can't get it off my mind, Allison.
It's obsessing me.
I'm getting tired of it.
I need your attention.
But it doesn't make any sense.
He drove past the book depository...
...and the police said conclusively
that it was an exit wound.
So how is it possible for Oswald
to have fired from two angles at once?
- It doesn't make sense!
- Alvy...
I'll tell you this.
He was not marksman enough...
...to hit a moving target at that range.
But...
...if there was a second assassin...
- That's it!
- We've been through this.
They recovered the shells from that rifle.
OK. What are you saying now?
Everybody on the Warren Commission
is in on this conspiracy, right?
Well, why not?
Yeah. Earl Warren?
Hey, honey. I don't know Earl Warren.
Lyndon Johnson?
Lyndon Johnson is a politician!
You know the ethics those guys have.
It's like a notch
underneath child molester.
Then everybody's in on the conspiracy.
The FBI and the CIA
and J Edgar Hoover and oil companies...
...and the Pentagon and the men's room
attendant at the White House.
I would leave out
the men's room attendant.
You're using this conspiracy theory
as an excuse to avoid sex with me.
Oh, my God!
She's right.
Why did I turn off Allison Portchnik?
She was beautiful, she was willing,
she was real intelligent.
Is it the old Groucho Marx joke that
I just don't wanna belong to any club...
...that would have
someone like me for a member?
Alvy, don't panic! Please stop it!
It's a mistake to ever bring
a live thing in the house.
Stop it! Go for that one there.
Maybe we should call the police.
Dial 911. It's the lobster squad.
They're only baby ones, for God's sakes.
- If they're only babies, you pick 'em up.
- All right! All right!
- Here you go!
- Don't give it to me! Don't!
Look! One crawled
behind the refrigerator.
It'll turn up in our bed at night.
Will you get out of here
with that thing? Jesus!
Talk to 'em. You speak shellfish.
Hey, look. Put it in the pot.
I can't put it in the pot!
I can't put a live thing in hot water!
You think we're gonna
take him to the movies?
Oh, good, Alvy. Oh, thank you.
OK. It's in. It's definitely in the pot.
Annie, there's a big lobster
behind the refrigerator.
I can't get it out. This thing's heavy.
Maybe if I put a dish of butter sauce here
with a nutcracker, it'll run out.
I'm gonna get my camera.
I think if I could pry the door off...
We should have gotten steaks.
They don't run around.
(Annie screams) Goddamn it! Oh, jeez!
Pick this lobster up. Hold it, please.
You're gonna take pictures now?
Alvy, it'll be wonderful. Oh, lovely!
Oh, God! That's disgusting!
One more, Alvy. Please!
Oh, good! Good!
Here's what I want to know.
Am I your first big romance?
Oh, no. No, no. Uh-uh.
Really? Who was?
There was Dennis
from Chippewa Falls High School.
(Alvy) Dennis? Local kid? Would
meet you in front of the movie house?
(Annie) You should have seen
how I looked then.
(Alvy) Oh, I can imagine.
The wife of an astronaut.
(Annie) Then there was Jerry, the actor.
Look at you. You're such a clown.
I look pretty.
You always look pretty. But that guy...
Acting is like an exploration of the soul.
It's very religious.
Like a kind of liberating consciousness.
It's like a visual poem.
Is he kidding with that crap?
Oh, right. (laughs)
I think I know exactly what you mean
when you say "religious".
You do?
- Oh, come on. I was younger.
- Hey, that was last year.
It's like when I think of dying.
- You know how I'd like to die?
- No. How?
I'd like to get torn apart by wild animals.
Heavy! Eaten by some squirrels!
Listen, he was a terrific actor.
He's neat-looking and he was emotional...
I don't think you like emotion too much.
Touch my heart... with your foot.
I may throw up.
(Annie) He was creepy.
(Alvy) I think you're pretty lucky
I came along.
(Annie) Oh, really? Well, la-de-da.
(Alvy) If anyone had ever told me
I would be taking out a girl...
...who used expressions like la-de-da...
(Annie) You really like
those New York girls.
- Well, not just. Not only.
- I'd say so. You married two of them.
There's Henry Drucker.
He has a chair in history at Princeton.
The short man is Hershel Kaminsky.
He has a chair in philosophy at Cornell.
Two more chairs,
they got a dining room set.
- Why are you so hostile?
- Cos I wanna watch the Knicks on TV.
Is that Paul Goodman? No.
Be nice to the host,
because he's pu