There was no one like Hal.
He met me at a party
and swept me off my feet.
"Blue Moon" was playing.
You know "Blue Moon?"
Sure.
I still remember that.
Oh.
âª Blue moon âªâª
And one more year
and I would have graduated.
But I quit BU to marry him. I mean,
what was I learning at school anyway?
I mean, can you picture me
as an anthropologist?
Is that a joke?
The sex was always great. Well,
he was nine years older than me.
He'd already made
and lost a fortune.
But then he made it back,
and more. I mean, much more.
God, he was dynamic.
Taught me everything I know
about real lovemaking,
not that I care to get too graphic.
Believe me when I tell you.
They tried six medications on me.
Cocktails, they call them.
The only cocktail that helped
was a Stoli martini.
I never trusted doctors.
Doctors put both my parents
in early graves.
I have never
been to San Francisco.
And Hal and I traveled everywhere.
I hear it's beautiful.
I'll be staying with my sister,
Ginger. She's divorced.
Biologically, she's not my sister.
She's adopted. We're both adopted.
I couldn't stand her ex-husband.
He used to hit her.
That's mine. The Vuitton.
My plan is to start a new life out here.
Hm.
Put everything behind me
and start fresh.
Go West. Was it Horace Greeley
who said that? "Go West."
Oh, there's my family.
It was really nice talking to you.
Oh, I'll call you,
maybe for lunch.
I don't have your number.
Who's that woman you were talking to?
I was sitting next to her on the plane.
She was talking to herself.
I thought she said something to me.
I said, "What?"
But she couldn't stop
babbling about her life.
Where--? Where am I exactly?
You said 305 South Van Ness.
- Can you wait, help me with my bags?
- Sure.
I don't know where she is.
She expected me.
The plane was on time.
Yes, I'm-- I'm--
You all right?
I'm fine. I just sometimes get
where I can't take a deep breath
and when I can, it makes me panic
and it makes it even worse.
Okay.
Could I have some privacy?
Sure, sure.
Hello, Ginger?
Yes, I'm here.
I'm right in front of the place.
It is 305?
Uh-huh.
Ugh. Well, how long?
What? Where is it?
No, no, I see it.
Okay. Oh, okay.
Just-- Would you please hurry?
My sister left the keys in the bar.
- Can you wait?
- Sure.
Is that it?
Thank you.
Oh, thank you.
Have a great day, all right?
Bye-bye.
So, what do you think?
I love it.
The fireplaces work. I don't
like when they're for show.
It's so light and airy
and the ceilings are so high.
How can anyone breathe
with a low ceiling? The view.
You wanted Fifth Avenue.
Central Park. Superb.
Oh, this space is perfect.
We hardly have to do a thing.
You shouldn't spoil me so.
Well, why not?
Who else am I gonna spoil?
Did I tell you my news?
What?
Danny is gonna be living with us.
Oh, honey.
Oh, that's great news.
I worked it out with his mom,
her lawyers.
Oh, he'll be so much happier
when he's with us full-time.
Happy birthday, Danny.
Kids at school say we're really rich
and that you give money to charity.
Sure I do. You gotta remember
as you go through life
to share what you earn
with the less fortunate.
Not everyone is as lucky
as we are.
Domingo?
Yes, ma'am.
Another bottle of the Margaux.
Sure.
Excuse me.
It would look perfect.
Wouldn't wash me out?
No, not at all.
Not the way he--
Oh, isn't he sweet?
This song was playing
when Hal and I first met.
- I fell in love with the name Jasmine.
- Oh, so romantic.
I changed it.
Yeah, Jeanette had no panache.
This song was playing
when we first met.
You know it? Yeah, we met
at a party at Martha's Vineyard.
"Blue Moon."
Come on, boys.
Okay, let's go, Augie.
I gotta get home. Someone's waiting.
We helped Dad
move the furniture today.
Oh, really? That's
your idea of taking the boys?
Letting them help you
lug somebody's furniture upstairs?
- They loved it. Great exercise.
- Yeah?
They-- We ate franks and beans.
- Yeah.
- Relax.
- Let's go, Johnny, come on.
- Come on. Let's go. Come on.
- What's the rush?
What's the rush, Ginger?
You got a date?
It's none of your business.
It happens to be Jeanette, so...
Jeanette?
Jasmine?
What is she doing in town?
She's living with me
till she gets back on her feet.
She's had a bad time. Yeah.
Uh-huh.
When she had money,
she wanted nothing to do with you.
Now that she's broke,
she's moving in.
She's not just broke.
She's screwed up.
And it's none of your damn
business. She's family.
She stole our money.
Okay.
Understand? We could have been set.
That was our whole chance in life.
For the last time, Augie,
he was the crook, not her, okay?
What the hell did she know
about finance?
Don't stand there and tell me that.
She's married to a guy for years,
up to his ass in phony real estate
and bank fraud.
She knew nothing about it?
Believe me, she knew, Ginger.
Okay? She knew.
But when all those diamonds
and minks were flying in,
she just looked the other way.
I don't think so, Augie.
You said it. You said to me,
"She's a phony and had to know."
Jasmine, your country
house is so beautiful.
See?
I'm sorry, but we need an answer on this.
I told you, you change the name
of the corporation.
Operate under Global Innovations.
I don't know if we can.
I think we can, actually.
- Pay out of the accounts in Amsterdam.
- Amsterdam.
Whenever I hear them, they're one
step ahead of the Justice Department.
Just hope your house is not bugged.
Ha, ha, ha.
Oh, I never pay attention
to Hal's business affairs.
I have no head
for that sort of thing.
We transfer to the old corporation?
We could. Perfectly legal.
It would be a mistake under that name.
Definitely get in trouble for that.
Just don't file a joint
tax return. Ha, ha, ha.
Don't say that. I sign anything.
I'm very trusting.
Famous last words.
It's called looking
the other way.
Jasmine. Oh, my God.
Oh.
Look at you.
Oh, I am so sorry for the wait.
Sorry, I think I'm in Paris.
It's okay.
No, it's fine.
Augie's day with the boys.
Well, no wonder you're late.
Hello. Matthew, is it?
Yeah.
Boys, say hello.
I told you about her, remember?
Hi, I'm Jasmine.
Shake hands. Okay, go play.
They're big.
I know.
I'm getting it first.
Quiet, you two.
Well, they're loud.
Stop running around.
Christ, this kid's got--
What the hell is it? ADD?
- Yeah. Your place is homey.
- Are you kidding me?
No, I mean, it's got a very--
Well, it's casual charm.
God, knock it off,
Jasmine.
I need to stay here for a while.
No, I do.
I'm out of cash.
Okay.
Couldn't pay my rent in Brooklyn.
Can you believe
I had to move out of my home,
take a place in Brooklyn?
But I'm dead broke. Really,
the government took everything.
And the lawyers.
And I can't be alone, Ginger.
I really get some bad thoughts
when I'm alone.
Well, you know, all I can say is,
you look great.
Oh. Now who's lying?
You do.
You know, I was up all last night.
I was so anxious
Yeah? about moving hem
I wasn't sure how angry you still were.
Oh, well...
Another drink? We're celebrating.
Of course, yeah.
Oh, the flight was bumpy.
Uh-huh.
I didn't eat anything on the plane.
Oh, the food was awful. Here it is.
I mean, you'd think
first class, right?
You flew first class?
I don't know how anyone puts up
with those airlines.
Isn't first class a fortune?
Yes, I was quite shocked.
I thought you were tapped out.
I'm worse than tapped out, baby.
I've run up some serious debts.
So how did you fly first class?
I don't know, Ginger.
I just did.
All I meant was, if you've got
no money, to go first class...
You know me.
I splurge from habit.
Would you stop staring
at my luggage?
Yes, it's Louis Vuitton.
You told me you had to sell everything.
Look, look, look.
These are used, old suitcases.
See, with my initials. Who'd want them?
I sold what jewels and furs
I could hide from Uncle Sam.
God, I hate to tell you about that.
Jewelry is priceless, a great investment
when you buy it at Graff or Van Cleef
until you're desperate for money
and forced to sell,
and then it seems
you can't give it away.
Kids, stop it, come on!
- Were you adopted?
- Yes.
We were both adopted.
Born to different moms and dads, but
raised by the same morn and dad.
Could you stop doing
that gun thing? Sorry.
- Got migraine from the pressurized cabin.
- Matthew.
Did you like
the new mom and dad?
Yes, of course--
Aunt Jasmine did.
I ran away from home as fast
as my feet could carry me.
How come?
Well--
Our mother liked Aunt Jasmine
and not me.
Oh, stop.
How come?
She had better genes.
Don't tell them that.
Well, am I lying?
Dad said you're glad we lived far away.
What?
They're perfect for the dress
that I'm wearing to the Met Gala.
What's the matter?
Your mind is a million miles away.
Oh, I'm sorry. No, I-- I just got
a call from my sister, Ginger.
Oh, God, she's coming to New York
for a week with her husband, Augie.
He is a piece of work.
I just-- I don't know,
I guess I have to see them.
The one in San Francisco, the builder?
Yeah.
Oh, no, he's a contractor. I mean,
he's-- No, he's a handyman.
No, don't get me wrong.
I love Ginger, I do. She's a dear.
But our paths just went
in totally different directions.
Okay, that happens.
It's terrible of me to say,
but she was never too bright.
You know? And she was so wild
and I, of course, was Miss Perfect.
- Hi.
- Oh, you made it.
How lovely to see you.
Hi. Oh, my God.
Welcome.
Hi. Thank you.
Oh, this is my husband, Augie.
Augie.
This is Jeanette.
Jasmine. I changed it.
Jasmine.
I'm finally getting to meet the sister.
I know. Hello. I'm so sorry we
couldn't make it to the wedding.
Just that Hal had some
business in Saint-Tropez.
Couldn't get back in time.
Know what?
You missed a nice little party.
My friend Dennis sang.
He's great. Dennis Rackabuto.
I know. Hey--
Hal! You remember
Ginger.
Oh, my gosh.
How are you?
This is Augie.
Augie. How you doing?
Awesome.
Hell of a place you got.
Thank you.
Why don't you come through?
Told you.
- Yvette, coffee?
- This is really...
Yeah, she's got taste.
It's like what
you see in the movies.
We have so much to catch up on. Can't
wait for you to show us New York.
Why don't you take
our car and driver?
Well, I hope you're gonna come.
I mean, how often am I here?
- No, no, I will definitely make some time.
- Oh, good. Heh, heh.
Where are you staying?
Oh, well, we-- We thought about
asking if we could stay with you,
but we don't wanna impose,
so we got a room at the Marriott.
Oh, the Marriott's perfect.
Oh. Yeah.
I'll have my office contact them
and forward us the bill.
Oh, no.
No, no, no, it's not necessary.
Please, you're our guests.
I insist.
Oh, well, then we insist
on taking you two to dinner tonight.
- What? Tonight?
- Yeah.
We have dinner plans.
I don't think we can--
Something we can't get out of.
I'm sorry' GINGER: There'll be time.
We stashed the kids with Augie's
sister, we're here for a week.
It's gonna be great.
It is. Okay.
Well, we don't have
a lot of free time,
but we'll definitely take you
to Le Cirque, won't we?
I mean, or Daniel. I mean--
They'd get a kick out of that.
Yeah, absolutely.
I know your birthday is this week.
Let us at least take you out for that.
I love how you're doing your hair.
Oh, thanks. Heh, heh.
You'll have to take me shopping. You
always could pick clothes. Heh, heh.
And Augie's got
some exciting business news
he wants to talk to Hal about.
Oh?
Don't worry, I don't need to
borrow money. We're flush.
Yeah,
What kind of work do you do, Augie?
Well, you know, I do, like,
repairs, furniture moving,
but I got plans to be
my own boss.
We'll talk about it over dinner.
They're going out.
Hey, could we have a tour?
Oh, yeah, of course. Why don't
you start in the kitchen?
Is there a little girls' room?
Just down the hall.
Wow.
Five days.
I'll have to invite them
to my birthday party now.
Where did she come up with him?
I always feel so guilty around Ginger.
We've got to make sure
we make their stay extra nice.
My God, five days.
Look.
It's so beautiful.
Oh.
Oh, but where would I wear
a Fendi bag?
Oh, go ahead. It's my treat.
No.
Yeah.
Really?
Oh, my God. I love it. Look.
Look.
Take the other one off.
No, I like this.
Boy, this is some place
you got here.
- I mean, this is unreal.
- It is.
Reminds me
of when I was a kid.
I used to be a lifeguard.
Start your own construction
company? Great idea.
We came into some money.
Tell him how, Augie.
What? We've been saving this story.
Well, the first 10-, 12,000,
I really worked for.
Put away a little each week.
But he's not
telling you the big news.
Why we're in New York.
You tell them.
Okay, I will.
We always play the lottery,
and we never even get two numbers.
Am I right?
Uh-huh.
But last week, we hit it.
We got 200,000 bucks.
Oh, that's fantastic.
I thought I'd drop dead.
That's great.
I never held that kind of money
in my hands. I mean, ever.
He was shaking
when we won.
Me? You had to see her. I had to tell
her, this is a once-in-a-lifetime.
Congratulations.
Yeah.
He wants to begin a business.
What do you think?
Well, if you like, I think Hal could
probably help you do better.
Yeah?
You know-- You know, I'm no gambler.
I mean, not with my one chance to--
Hey, come on. We don't know the first
thing about money, but he does.
First thing is how not to give half
your money to the government.
Look, I know there's taxes,
but, I mean, what can I do?
- There are ways.
- You see, Augie? You see?
Suppose I put you in a venture
that was low-risk, but very high-yield.
I'm not talking about 6 or 7 percent.
I'm talking about 20 percent.
Profitable enough?
20 percent?
He's developing a group of hotels
in the Caribbean.
You mean, not starting
my own business.
No, we mean investing with Hal.
Jeez, investing what?
You mean the whole thing?
You need money to make money.
Am I right?
Ginger.
Let them in on one of your--?
The hotel deal or something.
It'd be great for them.
Make a killing.
Pay attention, Augie.
I'm paying attention.
You will make money for them,
won't you?
I make money,
they make money.
God, they're hard work.
Tomorrow I'm taking
the day off.
I've neglected everything,
my yoga, my Pilates.
I've got that luncheon to plan,
the fundraiser
for the Central Park Conservancy.
I've rented them a limo
and a driver,
and I've suggested they go
to the South Street Seaport.
Can you imagine
if they lived here?
Here, for doing your duty.
Happy birthday.
Oh.
I'm giving it to you now so you can
wear it to your party tomorrow night.
Oh, sweetheart, it's beautiful.
Not bad taste for
a philistine businessman, huh?
âª A good man is hard to find âª
âª Well, you always get the other kind âª
âª And just when you think
He's your one best pal âª
âª You look around
You find him lovin' another gal âª
âª You rave
Yes, you crave âª
âª To see that man laying in his grave âª
âª So if your man is nice
Take my advice âª
âª And hug him in the morning
Hug him every night âª
âª Give him plenty lovin'
Be sure you love him right âª
âª 'Cause a good man nowadays
Is hard to find âªâª
I know, it's so extravagant.
Oh, look at that.
He surprised me in the tub, so to speak.
Ha, ha, ha.
Corsica's a bore. The weather's nice,
but it's nothing like Sardinia.
This year you are coming
to Palm Beach, no excuses.
Hey, Jasmine.
What?
Who's that woman?
Which?
That one.
Oh, Raylene.
She's a friend.
I love Raylene.
We met in a yoga class.
Isn't she pretty?
Yeah.
She runs a modeling agency.
How long have you known her?
Few years. Why?
- And you trust her?
- Trust her?
Of course I trust her.
What kind of question is that?
She just seems so cozy all night
with your husband.
I wouldn't worry. Hal's not
the roving type, nor is Raylene.
She's a very close friend.
I don't know.
If it was my husband,
I'd keep an eye on him.
Goodness,
you are a suspicious one.
I'm just saying.
Just relax.
I am relaxed.
You shouldn't drink
so much, Augie.
Nobody wants to hear those
stupid Polish jokes, you know?
Oh, I had a drink?
Yeah? Yeah.
Let me tell you, you were half in
the bag the entire night, okay?
Tell me about my drinking.
Give me that.
What's eating you?
If you saw your friend's wife kissing
another guy, would you tell your friend?
Hey.
What?
Would you tell your friend?
I'm talking.
Tell him what?
Are you listening to me?
If you saw your friend's wife kissing
another guy, would you tell your friend?
Would you tell him?
Yeah.
Bet your ass I'd tell him.
But what if it causes trouble?
Or maybe a divorce?
If you don't say anything,
it could've been a passing thing.
He never knows and he lives on
happy with his wife.
You know, I would tell him,
because that's what a friend's for.
You gotta have his back.
That's why I'd tell him.
It's a tough call, Augie.
I don't know.
Ginger.
What?
What are we doing?
Are we playing charades?
I mean, come on.
Did you see something?
Yeah.
On the street, by accident.