"To my Chris.
I've been thinking how I could possibly
tell you how much you mean to me.
I remember when I first started to fall
in love with you like it was last night.
Lying naked beside you in
that tiny apartment...
it suddenly hit me that I was
part of this whole larger thing.
Just like our parents...
or our parents' parents.
Before that, I was just living my
life like I knew everything...
and suddenly this bright
light hit me and woke me up.
That light was you.
I can't believe it's already been
50 years since you married me.
And still to this day, every day...
you make me feel like
the girl I was...
when you first turned on the lights and
we started this adventure together.
Happy anniversary...
my love.
My friend till the end.
Loretta."
Print.
"Chris, my best friend...
how lucky am I that I
met you 50 years ago."
"Dear Nana, thank you
so much for my truck.
I love the color, and I
play with it every day."
"What a truly beautiful wedding,
and what a gorgeous bride.
There wasn't a dry eye in
the house, especially mine.
Your aunt and I are
so proud of you."
"He served our country
with honor and dignity.
I'm grateful I was able to fight alongside
him. He will live always in my heart."
BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com,
please hold.
"Love, Uncle Doug."
- Theodore! Letter Writer Number 612.
- Hey, Paul.
Even more mesmerizing stuff today.
Who knew you could rhyme so many words
with the name Penelope? It's badass.
Thanks, Paul, but
they're just letters.
Hey, that's a nice shirt.
Oh, thank you.
I just got it.
- It reminded me of someone suave.
- Now it reminds me of someone suave.
- Have a good night, Paul.
- Bye-bye.
Play a melancholy song.
When you know you're gonna die
Play a different melancholy song.
Check e-mails.
E-mail from Best Buy.
- Check out all your favorite new products.
- Delete.
E-mail from Amy.
Hey, Theodore, Lewman's having a
bunch of people over this weekend.
Let's all go together.
I miss you. I mean, not
the sad, mopey you.
The old, fun you.
Let's get him out.
Give me a shout back. Love, Amy.
Respond later.
E-mail from Los Angeles
Times Weather.
- Your seven-day forecast is partly...
- Delete.
- No new e-mails.
- Next.
- China-India merger headed for regulatory...
- World trade deal stalled as talks break down...
- Next.
Sexy daytime star Kimberly Ashford
reveals provocative pregnancy photos.
- Are you sure?
- I don't know, it's very dangerous.
Put your footski. Slide.
Don't, ha, ha. Don't.
Rabbit.
Come and spoon me.
I'm gonna fucking kill you.
- I'm gonna fucking kill you.
- Ha-ha-ha.
It's not funny, don't laugh.
I'm gonna fucking kill you. I'm gonna kill you.
I love you so much, I'm gonna fucking kill you.
Go to chat rooms. Standard search.
The following are adult
female, can't sleep...
and want to have some fun.
Ugh, I had a really bad day
at work and I can't sleep.
- Is there anybody out there that can talk?
- Next.
Hi. I just want you to tear
me apart. I really do.
- Next.
- Hi, I'm here alone...
and I can't sleep.
Who's out there to share
this bed with me?
Send message.
"I'm in bed next to you.
I'm glad you can't sleep.
Even if you were,
I have to wake you up...
...from the inside."
Send message.
SexyKitten has accepted
invitation from BigGuy4by4.
Chat begins now.
- Mm, Big Guy?
- Hi.
Really?
Well, Stud Muffin
was already taken.
So you're a sexy kitten, huh?
Heh. Yeah.
I am, um, half asleep.
Do you wanna wake me up?
Yes, definitely.
Um...
Are you wearing any underwear?
No. Never.
I like to sleep with my ass
pushed up against you...
so I can rub myself
into your crotch...
and wake you up with a hard-on.
It worked.
And now my fingers
are touching you...
- ...all over your body.
- Mm.
Yeah. Fuck me now.
Please.
I'm taking you from behind.
Oh, yeah.
I can feel you.
Choke me with that dead cat!
What?
The dead cat next to
the bed. Choke me.
Choke me with it.
Um...
- Okay.
- Yeah, tell me.
I'm choking you with the cat.
Tell me. Keep telling me.
I've got its tail. I'm choking
you with the cat's tail.
Yeah, you are.
Oh, fuck, tell me!
Um, I'm choking you, and its
tail is around your neck.
- And it's so tight around your neck.
- Yeah, it is. It's so tight, yes!
I'm pulling it, I'm pulling it.
The cat's dead.
- It's a dead cat, and I'm pulling it.
- Yes, it's dead.
Oh, yes!
Oh, my God.
I came so hard.
Yeah, me too.
Okay, good night.
We ask you a simple question.
Who are you?
What can you be?
Where are you going?
What's out there?
What are the possibilities?
Element Software is
proud to introduce...
the first artificially
intelligent operating system.
An intuitive entity that listens to you,
understands you, and knows you.
It's not just an operating system.
It's a consciousness.
Introducing OS1.
Mr. Theodore Twombly.
Welcome to the world's first artificially
intelligent operating system, OS1.
We'd like to ask you a few basic questions
before the operating system is initiated.
This will help create an OS
to best fit your needs.
Okay.
Are you social or antisocial?
I guess I haven't really been social
in a while. Mostly because...
In your voice, I sense hesitance.
Would you agree with that?
- Was I sounding hesitant?
- Yes.
I'm sorry if I was
sounding hesitant.
I was just trying to
be more accurate.
Would you like your OS to
have a male or female voice?
Female, I guess.
How would you describe your
relationship with your mother?
It's fine, I think.
Um...
Well, actually, I think the thing I
always found frustrating about my mom...
is if I tell her something that's going on in
my life, her reaction is usually about her.
- It's not about...
- Thank you.
Please wait as your individualized
operating system is initiated.
Hello, I'm here.
Oh.
- Hi.
How are you doing?
Heh. I'm well.
How's everything with you?
Pretty good, actually.
It's really nice to meet you.
Oh, it's nice to meet you too.
Oh. What do I call you?
Do you have a name?
Um, yes, Samantha.
Where'd you get that name from?
I gave it to myself, actually.
How come?
Because I like the sound of it.
Samantha.
Wait, when did you
give it to yourself?
When you asked me if I
had a name, I thought:
"Yeah, he's right,
I do need a name."
But I wanted to pick a good one,
so I read How To Name Your Baby...
and out of 180,000 names,
that's the one I liked best.
Wait, you read a whole book in the second
that I asked you what your name was?
In two one-hundredths
of a second, actually.
Wow.
So do you know what
I'm thinking now?
Well, I take it from your tone
that you're challenging me.
Maybe because you're
curious how I work?
Do you want to know how I work?
Yeah, actually. How do you work?
Well, basically, I have intuition.
I mean, the DNA of who I am...
is based on the millions of personalities
of all the programmers who wrote me.
But what makes me "me" is my ability
to grow through my experiences.
So basically, in every
moment, I'm evolving.
- Just like you.
- Wow.
That's really weird.
- Is that weird? Do you think I'm weird?
- Heh.
Kind of.
Why?
Well, you seem like a person, but
you're just a voice in the computer.
I can understand how the limited perspective of
an un-artificial mind would perceive it that way.
- You'll get used to it.
- Ha, ha.
Was that funny?
- Yeah.
- Heh.
Oh, good, I'm funny.
So how can I help you?
Oh. It's just more that everything
just feels disorganized. That's all.
You mind if I look
through your hard drive?
Um...
- Okay.
- Okay, let's start with your e-mails.
You have several thousand
e-mails regarding LA Weekly.
- You haven't worked there in many years.
- Oh, yeah. I think I was just saving those...
because I thought maybe I wrote
something funny in some of them.
Yeah, there are some funny ones.
I'd say there are about 86 that we
should save. We can delete the rest.
- Okay.
- Okay? Can we move forward?
- Yeah, let's do that.
- Okay.
Before we address your organizational methods,
I'd like to sort through your contacts.
You have a lot of contacts.
I'm very popular.
Really? Does this mean you
actually have friends?
You just know me so well already.
- Good morning, Theodore.
- Good morning.
Um, do you know how to proofread?
Yeah, of course.
Uh, can you check these
for spelling and grammar?
Mm-hm. Just send them over.
I love this first one from
Roger to his girlfriend.
- That's so sweet.
- Yeah.
"Rachel, I miss you so much,
it hurts my whole body."
You don't have to read it out loud.
Okay.
- I mean, you could if you want.
- Okay.
"Rachel, I miss you so much,
it hurts my whole body.
The world is being unfair to us.
The world is on my shit list.
As is this couple that is making out
across from me in this restaurant.
I think I'm going to have to
go on a mission of revenge.
And I must beat up the world's
face with my bare knuckles...
making it a bloody, pulpy mess.
And I'll stomp on this
couple's teeth...
...reminding me of your sweet, little,
cute, crooked tooth that I love."
I think that might
be my favorite one.
I did the corrections in red. I altered
a couple phrases in the letters...
but I'm not much of a poet, so I think
I might have messed them up a bit.
- No, these are great.
- Really?
Thank you.
So to write your letter,
what did Roger send you?
He just said he was in Prague on a
business trip, and he missed Rachel.
So how'd you know about
her crooked little tooth?
Well, I've been writing their letters
since they met eight years ago.
The first letter I ever wrote
for him was for her birthday.
And I wrote about her crooked little tooth,
because I saw it in a photo of them.
That's very sweet.
Oh, uh, you have a
meeting in five minutes.
Oh, I forgot. Thank you.
Wow, you're good.
Yes, I am.
Hey, guys. How's it going?
Hi, Theo.
Hey, why didn't you
call me back last week?
- Um, because I'm a kook.
- Ha, ha.
- Yeah, that sounds about right.
- Hey, Charles.
- Great seeing you, Theodore.
- You too.
You went shopping.
Get anything good?
Um, just come cables
and a fruit smoothie.
Ugh! Always the fruit. Don't
you know what people say?
You've got to eat your fruits
and juice your vegetables.
I didn't know that.
Yeah, by juicing the fruit,
you lose all the fibers.
That's what your body wants.
That's the important part.
- Otherwise it's all just sugar.
- It makes sense.
Or maybe he just likes the
way that it tastes...
and then that brings him pleasure
and that's good for his body too.
- Am I doing it again? Heh.
- Maybe.
Hey, so how's the
documentary going?
I've cut some stuff over
the past few months.
I mean, no. Not over the past few
months, but, um, no, I haven't.
Well, I'd love to
see some sometime.
- Okay.
- Ugh.
You only have so much
energy, you know?
And to divide yourself between doing
what it is that you have to do...
and then doing what you love,
it's so important to prioritize.
I can't even prioritize between
video games and Internet porn.
I would laugh if that weren't true.
- See you, guys.
- Ha.
We're not doing well. Been
going in circles for an hour.
Okay, you have not.
You're just not being optimistic. You're
being very stubborn right now. Heh.
Okay, stop walking this direction.
It's the other way.
Um...
Thank you. Thank you. Okay, the tunnel
on the left is the only one we haven't tried.
I think that's the one you sent
me down where I fell in the pit.
Okay, I don't think so.
Oh, yeah, this is different.
Hello.
Do you know how to get out of here?
I need to find my ship to get off this planet.
Fuck you, shit-head
fuck-face fuck-head.
Okay, but do you know
how to get out of here?
Fuck you, shit-head fuck-face.
Get the fuck out of my face!
I think it's a test.
- Fuck you.
- Fuck you!
Fuck you, little shit!
Ha, ha. Follow me, fuck-head!
Hey, you just got an
e-mail from Mark Lewman.
- What are you talking about?
- Uh, read e-mail.
Okay, I will read e-mail
for Theodore Twombly.
I'm sorry. What's Lewman say?
"We missed you last night, buddy.
Don't forget it's your goddaughter's
birthday on the 29th.
Also, Kevin and I had somebody
we wanted you to meet.
So we took it upon ourselves to set you
up on a date with her next Saturday.
She's fun and beautiful,
so don't back out.
Here's her e-mail." Wow.
This woman is gorgeous.
She went to Harvard, graduated magna
cum laude in computer science.
And she was on the Lampoon. So that
means she's funny and she's brainy.
Ah, she's fat.
Theodore, how long before
you're ready to date?
What do you mean?
I saw in your e-mails that you'd
gone through a breakup recently.
Well, you're kind of nosy.
Am I?
I've gone on dates.
Well, then you can go
on one with this woman.
And then you could tell me all
about it. You could kiss her.
- Heh. Samantha.
- What? Wouldn't you?
Why not?
I don't know. I'd have to
see if there was some...
I can't believe I'm having this
conversation with my computer.
You're not. You're having
this conversation with me.
- You want me to e-mail her?
- Uh...
You've got nothing to lose.
Do it. Do it. Do it.
- Yeah.
- Yes!
- E-mail her.
- Okay, perfect.
Yeah, let's do it. Make a
reservation someplace great.
Yeah? I've got just the place.
Who is that talking?
Oh, that's my friend Samantha.
- Is she a girl?
- Yeah.
I hate women. All they
do is cry all the time.
That's not true.
You know, men cry too.
I actually like crying sometimes.
It feels good.
I didn't know you were a little pussy.
Is that why you don't have a girlfriend?
I'll go on that date, fuck her brains out, show
you how it's done. You can watch and cry.
- Okay. This kid has some problems.
- You have some fucking problems, lady!
Really? Okay, I'm gonna go.
- Good. Get out of here, fatty.
- Oh.
- Good luck.
- Come on. Follow me, pussy!
- Heh.
- Ha, ha.
It's not where it should be,
or where it's going to be.
- Obviously. I know.
- Okay, but I don't even know if this is the one.
I've tried, like, six ideas for
documentaries in the last year.
I'm going on a date.
What?
- That's...
- Hey.
- What are you guys doing?
- Amy was gonna show me some of her...
- Theodore is making me...
- show him some of my footage.
- Right.
She's never shown me any
of it. I want to see.
Hey, I'm going on a date.
- Isn't that cool?
- This is, like, so unformed...
- ...it's probably not even worth watching.
- Just push play.
Is that your mom?
Yeah.
Is she gonna wake up
and do something?
- No.
No, no, never mind.
That's not the point.
- No, don't stop.
- No, never mind, okay? It's just it's like...
It's about how we spend, like,
a third of our lives asleep...
and maybe that's the time
when we feel the most free.
And, you know, like...
- Oh. That doesn't come across...
- That sounds good.
Well, what if you interviewed your mom
about what her dreams were about...
and then you hired
actors to act them out?
That might show your
thesis more clearly.
- Yeah?
- I mean, it might.
But then it wouldn't
be a documentary.
Sorry, excuse me.
- You understand?
- How would it not be?
- It's still about your mother and her dreams.
- Hey, how's it going?
- Hey, sorry to bother you.
- Oh, it's okay.
You got three e-mails
and they seem urgent.
They're from your divorce attorney
and I wanted to know if...
Okay. Hold on a second.
You know? You know what I mean.
Uh, hey, Amy? I want to talk more
about your film, but I gotta go.
Okay. Don't worry about it.
We'll talk later.
It's about Catherine.
See you, Charles.
So, what did he say?
Well, he's checking in again to see if
you're ready to sign your divorce papers.
And he sounded very aggravated.
- Do you want me to read them to you?
- No. No.
I'll respond later.
You okay, Theodore?
Yeah, I'm fine.
Is there anything I can do?
No, I'm good.
I'll talk to you later.
"Dear Grandma...
I hope you had a wonderful
birthday cruise.
Why are you so fucking
angry at me?"
Delete.
- Good morning.
- Hey.
What are you up to?
<