(CAR ENGINE RUNNING)
ABE: Kant said human reason is troubled by
questions that it cannot dismiss,
but also cannot answer.
Okay, so, what are we talking about here?
Morality? Choice?
The randomness of life?
Aesthetics? Murder?
JILL: I think Abe was crazy
from the beginning.
Was it from stress? Was it anger?
Was he disgusted by what he saw
as life's never-ending suffering?
Or was he simply bored
by the meaninglessness
of day-to-day existence?
He was so damn interesting.
And different.
And a good talker.
And he could always
cloud the issue with words.
ABE: Where to begin?
You know, the existentialists
feel nothing happens
until you hit absolute rock bottom.
Well, let's say that when I went
to teach at Braylin College,
emotionally, I was at Zabriskie Point.
Of course, my reputation,
or should I say a reputation, preceded me.
JOE: I hear Abe Lucas is gonna be
joinin' the faculty this summer.
JUDY: Really?
That should put some Viagra
into the philosophy department.
He's this really interesting guy,
but he looks totally wasted.
I kind of like the burned-out look, though.
Oh, my God, me too.
Well, yeah, and he has affairs
with some of his students, I heard.
- Really?
- Yeah, like full... Yeah.
Abe Lucas is teaching
my Ethical Strategies class
for summer session.
- Have you read any of his papers?
- Mmm-hmm.
He's very radical.
Very original.
You either love him or hate him, really.
Faye Cohen knows someone who knows him,
but she says, he had a serious depression
when his wife left him.
The story is,
she ran off with his best friend.
Really?
'Cause, actually,
what I heard through the rumor mill
was he had a breakdown
when his best friend was killed.
He was a TV crew guy in Iraq
and he got beheaded.
Isn't that gruesome if it's true?
Jesus, I haven't even met the guy yet,
and I'm already jealous.
(CHUCKLING) Jealous?
I love that you're jealous.
That makes me feel desired.
Oh, God, you don't have to worry.
Everybody on campus desires you.
- Oh, come on.
- But I have you.
I don't know, suddenly the thought of you
coming under the spell
of some charismatic professor...
Oh, God, you don't have to worry.
I'm under your spell.
Good. Let's keep it that way.
- Yeah?
- Mmm-hmm.
Excuse me.
Uh, do you know where Jessup Hall is?
Yes, Jessup Hall is that building
over there, the red one.
Uh-huh, all right.
Thank you.
ASSISTANT: Doctor Reed?
- Oh.
- ASSISTANT: Professor Lucas.
- Professor Lucas, welcome to Braylin.
- Thank you.
- Are you okay?
- Yes.
- I'm sure you've had a long trip.
- Mmm-hmm. It was, yeah.
- Well, um...
- Thank you.
We've just concluded our spring semester,
and summer's always very active at Braylin.
(SIGHING) Uh-huh.
We're all very happy to have you here
in the philosophy department.
Mmm, thank you.
This is it.
Now, the faculty housing
is pretty much spread out,
but, you know, everything you can get to.
It's within walking distance of the campus.
And you're really gonna like Newport.
It's beautiful here, but it gets
a little crowded in the summer.
That can be a drag.
It's a small house,
but it's really comfortable.
Um, right over here is the living room,
and there's a little kitchen that way.
And there's a little dining room
right next to that.
Upstairs...
This way.
Bathroom to the right.
And this is the bedroom.
It's small, but really comfortable.
And there's an office over there.
I think you'll really love
the philosophy department, you know?
It's in this old,
beautiful part of the campus.
And there's a more modern wing,
that's got state-of-the-art
stuff for science,
and computer technology,
if you're into that.
Oh, and if you want to go away,
we're just 45 minutes from Providence.
Thank you.
Do you want a drink?
(CHUCKLING) Oh, no! God, no.
There's a little cocktail reception
to welcome you at 6:00.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
You know, I have to tell you,
I loved your essay on situational ethics.
Oh, I'm glad you liked it.
It caused a little, uh, static
with the philosophy department at Adair.
- This is my husband, Paul.
- Hey, how you doin'?
- This is Abe Lucas, philosophy department.
- BOTH: Good to meet you.
- Yeah.
- How you doin' on that?
I'd like another one, please.
- What is it?
- Vodka martini, extra olives.
- Anything for you?
- Sure, I'll have another.
- Uh, scotch?
- Mmm-hmm.
- Okay.
- Thank you.
I'm Rita Richards.
It's so good to have you here.
Hey, if you're ever bored
and you want someone to give you
the real lowdown of
who's fucking who at this college,
just let me know.
So, Kant would argue
that in a truly moral world,
there is absolutely no room for lying.
And even the smallest lie
destroys his precious
categorical imperative.
So, Kant would say,
if a killer came to your house,
looking to kill the man hiding upstairs
and asked where he was,
you'd be obliged to tell him.
In his perfect world,
you know, you couldn't lie.
Yeah, I can see the logic
that if you open the door,
even just a crack,
you accept a world where
lying is permitted.
Uh-huh.
Okay, then, then you'd say
if the Nazis came to your house,
hiding Anne Frank and her family,
and asked if anyone
was in the attic, you'd say,
(IMITATING GERMAN ACCENT)
"Ja, the Franks are upstairs."
I doubt it.
Because there's a difference between
a theoretical world of philosophy bullshit,
and real life, you know?
Real, nasty, ugly life
that includes greed,
and hate, and genocide.
Remember,
if you learn nothing else from me,
you should learn that much of philosophy
is verbal masturbation.
EDGAR: Have you talked to him at all?
MS. LEONARD: Mmm.
You know, I asked him
if he wanted to eat with us.
- I like the guy, but he's in a world...
- He likes to eat alone.
Yeah, he's in a world all his own.
I think he likes to keep to himself a bit.
Uh, yeah, I guess so.
Yeah, so, let him be. Right?
- Could take some time.
- Right.
ABE: Okay, Kierkegaard.
Um...
You know, when making everyday decisions,
we have absolute freedom of choice.
All right?
You can do nothing, or anything.
And this feeling of freedom
creates a sense of dread.
A dizzy feeling.
Anxiety is the dizziness of freedom.
RITA: The students love you,
but, of course, you've raised
some eyebrows with the faculty.
- Do you ever get discouraged teaching?
- No.
You don't ever ask yourself
what the hell is it all about?
Mmm-mmm.
Another school, another batch of kids.
Sweet kids.
Mmm. Average kids.
Nice, but mostly mediocre.
They'll grow up to be those people
who shape the world with their ignorance
or misinformation, or passivity.
- Are you okay?
- Hmm?
- Yeah, yeah.
You want to come in?
This is where I live.
Paul's in Aspen at a symposium.
I've got great grass.
- (CLICKS TONGUE) Some other time.
- Are you sure?
Yeah.
Thanks. Thanks anyway.
I'll see you.
Tomorrow we're gonna discuss
phenomenology and Husserl.
So, be sure you do the reading, you know?
It can get a little complicated.
All right?
Hi, you wanted to see me?
Yes, your paper was quite good.
- Really?
- Yes.
I read so many papers and,
usually the students are merely
paraphrasing what they've read,
but I found your thinking
fresh and well-presented.
Oh, thank you.
I'm flattered.
I have to say, I was very influenced by
your ideas on randomness and chance.
Well, the truth is,
what I found most exciting
was when you took issue with my ideas.
When you disagreed with me,
your arguments were
well-reasoned and original.
(LAUGHING) Am I blushing right now?
That's a really big compliment.
Thank you.
Um, I did actually find
some parts of your book
a little hard to follow though,
and I would love if you
could explain some things to me.
Sure, can we get out of here,
though, before I die of suffocation?
I found your view of existence
too bleak for me.
It was like there were
no redeeming joys or pleasures.
Okay.
Why are you taking philosophy?
What do you want out of it?
Because if your goal is
to try and figure out
what all this bullshit's about, forget it.
You write books, you write papers.
You've done so much.
Well, let me tell you, when I look back
at all that verbal posturing,
my group thought we were
going to be so special.
I marched in every bullshit
political demonstration.
I spent six months in Darfur
getting food to starving families,
I wind up with meningitis.
- Mmm.
- I was in Bangladesh.
Yeah, you know, you want to see
a difference, to save the world.
(SIGHING) But when you see
what you're up against...
Do you like vintage single malt?
You drink?
You mean here?
- Yeah.
- (CHUCKLING) Right now?
(CHUCKLING) No, no, I couldn't.
JILL: There was no way I could have
realized from that first conversation
that a lot was very wrong with Abe.
He was so damn fascinating and vulnerable,
and I must say, I found him attractive.
I guess it helped that
he felt comfortable with me.
I drove a cab.
- I was a handyman in a building.
- (CHUCKLES)
I ran an elevator.
But I always read.
Always, always loved the Russian writers.
Especially Dostoyevsky.
Dostoyevsky got it.
I've read all of it.
- Really?
- Mmm.
JILL: Oh, I had a great conversation
with Abe Lucas the other day.
Uh-huh.
He said my paper was
well-organized and original.
- All right.
- Right?
Yeah, I can see where this is goin'.
Oh, stop it, please.
He's just fascinating because he's brilliant,
but he's a sufferer.
Perfect. Great, you always
became attracted to the sufferers.
Right? That's how we first met.
He's a real sufferer, Roy.
You had shingles.
(CHUCKLES)
He was traumatized
when his best friend was killed in Iraq.
- He was a journalist, just horrifying.
- Didn't he get his head cut off?
His head cut off?
No, no, it was an explosion.
ROY: Oh.
God, it's amazing how people
embellish these stories.
You know, Abe actually says
that people just manufacture drama
so they can get through their lives
because they're so empty.
Can we just change the subject
of Abe Lucas, please?
You've been, like, singing
his praises for half an hour.
All right, well, then,
how about I sing yours?
- Okay. Yeah, yeah. Good.
- How's that?
I love you in that sweater.
Of course, you love me in this sweater.
You bought it for me.
Well, you look great in that shade of blue.
You really do.
You know Abe's mother committed suicide?
Abe again?
I mean, can you imagine?
He was 12.
She drank bleach!
It's so sad.
You know, Simone de Beauvoir pointed out,
and quite correctly,
that in a society shaped by men,
women are seen as relative beings
existing only in relationship to men.
- Hmm.
- You agree with that?
- I agree with that completely.
- Mmm-hmm.
I'm sure you've heard the rumors about you.
That you've had a lot of
experience with women.
You mean slept with.
You find that fulfilling?
Many women and one-night stands?
I did at the time.
It had a certain frantic quality.
One day, it stopped being exciting.
I couldn't find distraction anymore
in that usually reliable painkiller,
the orgasm.
Why not?
I couldn't remember the reason for living.
(SIGHING) And when I did,
it wasn't convincing.
That sounds scary.
It's very scary when
you run out of distractions.
Well, what if it wasn't a distraction?
What if you just decided
to commit yourself to one person?
If I met someone now,
I'm too far gone to appreciate her.
(SIGHING) I have to go to my piano lesson.
What are you doing on Friday night?
(SIGHING) Oh, I don't know.
Why?
I think you should come to a party.
- Uh...
- I do.
Roy and I will take you.
We can go and it'll...
There'll be music and it'll be fun.
There's a lot of students that like you.
- (CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
- There really are.
And I think it's better than
just wallowing in your room.
I don't think that's healthy.
You should think about it.
You want to come out?
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
(KNOCKING AT DOOR)
- Yes?
- Hi.
I'm sorry for dropping in so suddenly but,
I was shopping today at
the liquor store, and,
I came across these two very fine bottles
of single malt scotch,
and I got one for Paul and myself.
And I know how much
you love single malt scotch.
Oh, that was very thoughtful of you.
How much do I owe you?
(CHUCKLES)
Oh, God, no, I bought it for you.
Oh, thank you.
You could have waited to give it to me.
You didn't have to come in the rain.
I couldn't wait.
I was excited over it.
Will you have one with me?
I thought you'd never ask.
Um... Hmm.
What have you been doing?
I'm trying to finish this book
I started a long time ago.
- What's it about?
- About Heidegger and fascism.
Just what the world needs.
Another book about Heidegger and fascism.
How's it coming?
I'm blocked.
I can't write.
Why?
Oh, I...
I can't write 'cause I can't breathe.
What would get you breathing again?
(SIGHS)
I, you know...
The will to breathe.
- Hmm.
- Inspiration, you know?
You need a muse.
I have never needed a muse before.
(SIGHING)
I hope you're not gonna send me
back out into the rain
without sleeping with me.
I'm trying to write.
You're blocked.
I'm going to unblock you.
Or are you becoming infatuated with
that student you spend so much time with?
When the hurricane hit in New Orleans,
Abe went down there
and stayed for six weeks.
He said the problems
were completely overwhelming.
And the political red tape
and corruption was just a scandal.
He couldn't believe the amount
of stupidity and greed.
It was a scandal for George Bush.
JILL: Well, Abe was right there
in the thick of it,
trying to get something accomplished.
And meanwhile, his wife was
falling in love with his best friend.
- JILL'S MOM: Uh-huh.
- Can you believe that?
Abe really, really loved his wife.
They met on a trip to Machu Picchu
to see the ruins.
- They both experimented with mescaline.
- (JILL'S MOM GRUNTS)
He's actually tried every drug.
He hates them.
He's very conservative
in a kind of liberal way.
- It seems like he really opened up to you.
- Mmm-hmm.
JILL'S MOM: Everyone says
he's not easy to get to know.
Well, I definitely have not found that.
Hey, can we just get off
the topic of Abe Lucas?
I mean, I must say,
I'm not thrilled
that you invited him out
with us tomorrow night
without asking me first.
Well, he needs some human contact, Roy.
Otherwise, he just sits
in his room and broods.
Yeah, but you can see
why I might be jealous, no?
- That's silly.
- (CHUCKLES)
Famous last words.
I'm sorry.
I know it must have been a disappointment,
to say the least.
Have you tried any of the impotence drugs?
It's not physical.
And don't take it personally.
I haven't been able to perform
in nearly a year.
Have you seen a shrink?
'Cause I know a good one for that problem.
I keep hoping it'll come back
as mysteriously as it left.
I'm sorry I let you down.
No, I'm sorry.
I'm sure it's hell for you.
Thanks for the scotch.
(POP MUSIC PLAYING)
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
What are you doing over here?
Are you having one of your morbid insights
on the transient futility of human joy?
Is my face that grim?
I have never seen a de Kooning
in a private house.
- I know, so my parents got it at auction.
- It's gorgeous.
They're just starting to collect.
They're buying so much.
They got a Kitaj and a Warhol
at Sotheby's, like, last week.
No way!
I know, I know.
JANE: April, honestly,
are you afraid of getting robbed?
No, I mean the house
has alarms, like, all over.
- Show them what your father keeps.
- No.
- Come on, show them...
- I'm not gonna show it to them.
Oh, my God. You do this, like,
every time you come over here.
It's so weird.
We get it, the painting is fine,
the painting is all right.
- (ALL GASPING)
- For the burglars.
MARK: Yes, there it is!
- Come on, give me it, give!
- Oh, my God.
- ROY: Is it loaded?
- This is my baby.
- My baby? Oh, my God.
- (ALL LAUGHING)
No, it's not loaded. It's totally...
I'm taking the bullets out.
Do you shoot this?
APRIL: No, my dad takes it out
into the woods sometimes.
(OVERLAPPING CHATTER)
DANNY: Where they play Russian Roulette.
What's Russian Roulette?
(ALL LAUGHING)
- Just explain it.
- All right, fine.
Okay, so, you take a bullet.
(CHUCKLING) Take a bullet
and you put it in the chamber.
- Don't demonstrate it...
- Well, I'm not gonna do it!
So, you... Then you spin it around, right?
And, um, you hold it up to your head.
- You squeeze the trigger.
- JANE: Okay...
And you have five, no, you have
five to one odds that nothing will happen.
But if you're unlucky...
- (LAUGHING) You're just kind of...
- Very unlucky.
Why?
And why do they do this,
just for money, or what?
No, it's like, it's, the stakes are
so much higher than money.
- It's not about money.
- For what? For what end?
You know, you get like a real high
when you pull the trigger and...
- Danny, stop! Put that away.
- (ALL ARGUING)
Here, let me see this.
I don't like guns.
Jus