This is unbelievable!
Look at this!
There's no city like this in the world.
There never was!
You act like you've never been here before.
I don't get here often enough.
That's the problem.
Can you picture how drop-dead
gorgeous this city is in the rain?
Imagine this town in the '20s.
Paris in the '20s,
in the rain; the artists and writers.
Why does every city have to be in the rain?
What's wonderful about getting wet?
I mean, could you ever picture us
moving here after we're married?
Oh God, no.
I could never live out of the United States.
You know, if I'd stayed here
and written novels,
and not gotten, you know, caught up in that,
just, grinding out movie scripts...
I'll tell you something:
I would drop the house in Beverly Hills,
the pool, everything,
in a second.
I mean, look:
This is where Monet lived and painted.
We're 30 minutes from town.
Imagine the two of us settling here.
We could do it, I mean,
if my book turns out.
You're in love with a fantasy.
I'm in love with you.
We should get back to town.
We're meeting Mom and Dad for dinner.
Let's meet 'em.
There are our sightseers.
If I never see another charming
boulevard or bistro again, I...
- What a town!
- Yes. To visit.
I could see myself living here!
I feel like the Parisians kind of "get me. "
I can see myself just strolling
along the Left Bank with a,
you know, baguette under my arm,
headed to Café de Flore
to scribble away on my book.
What did Hemingway say?
He called it a "moveable feast. "
In this traffic, nothing moves.
Well, a toast to John's
new business venture here!
- Cheers!
- Congratulations.
- Thank you.
Well, I'll be perfectly frank.
I'm excited about this corporate merger between
our folks and the French company, but otherwise,
I'm not a big Francophile.
- John hates their politics.
- Certainly been no friend to the United States.
Well, I mean, you can't exactly blame them
for not following us down that rabbit's hole in Iraq.
- The whole Bush, you know,...
- Oh, please. Let's not get into this
- bad discussion again and again.
- Honey, honey. We're not getting into... By the way, it's
fine for your father and I to disagree.
That's what a democracy is.
Your father defends the right-wing
of the Republican party,
and I happen to think you almost got to be
- like, a demented lunatic, but it's like...
- Okay. Okay!
But it doesn't mean we don't
respect each other's views, am I right?
- Can we talk about the wedding plans?
- Yes! Please.
Let's do that.
- Your father is just...
- Inez?
- Huh? Carol?
- Hi.
Oh my G... What are you doing here?
- Nice to see you! Hi.
- Hey!
- How are you?
- Good, thanks.
Paul and Carol Bates, this is my mother
- and father, and, of course, you know Gail.
- Hi. Very nice to meet you.
Well, you... you didn't mention
you were going to be here.
No, it was sudden. Um...
Paul got invited to lecture at
the Sorbone. Sorbonne.
Oh, how wonderful!
Well, uh, Dad's here on business,
and we just decided to
- freeload along. - Yes.
- Oh.
That's great.
We can spend some time together.
Well, I think we have a
lot of commitments, but I'm sure it's...
- What?
- Well, what are doing tomorrow?
- We're driving to Verrsailles.
- Versailles...
- Versailles.
- Oh,
- I'm dying to see Versailles.
- Yeah!
But it's too... uh...
We're late... I think what we're...
Tomorrow we're locked in
to a lunch at Brasserie Lipp.
- Oh no, that's just...
- Yeah. Yeah, we are. That's already...
You know I actually had
a professor that dined there,
and saw James Joyce!
Yeah, you know, like a
million years ago, and
apparently, Joyce was eating
sauerkraut and frankfurters.
Is that...
That's the end of the story?
Well, I mean it's not a story.
It's like a detailed...
- We would LOVE to go to Versailles. Yes.
- Oh, good.
I hope you're not going to be
as antisocial tomorrow at Versailles.
- How was I antisocial?
- Oh, please!
I mean, you could totally tell you didn't want to go.
Well, I mean, they're your
friends, and I have to admit
I'm not quite as taken with them as you are.
He's brilliant.
You know, I had such a crush on him
in college, and Carol's very bright.
Well, he's a pseudo-intellectual.
- Just a little bit.
- Uh, Gil,
I hardly think he'd be lecturing at
the Sorbonne if he's a pseudo-intellectual.
You should give him your book to read.
Oh, come on. Why?
No, because he could critique your writing,
and maybe show you why you're
having so much trouble.
I'm having trouble because
I'm a Hollywood hack
who never gave actual
literature a real shot.
- Until now.
- Please... Gil...
Honey, just promise me something.
If this book... doesn't pan out,
that you'll stop
eating your brains out,
and just go back to doing
what you do best.
I mean, the studios adore you.
You're in demand...
Do you really want to give
it all up just to struggle?
- Well...
- Mmm?
Mmm?
Why would you... want to do that?
I believe Louis moved his court here,
uh, in 1682.
Originally, all this was swampland.
In fact, if I'm not mistaken,
uh... in Old French, the word "versailles"
means, uh, something like,
- "terrain were the weeds have been pulled. "
- Is that right?
Uh... The... uh, middle section here
uh... is... uh,
French classical style at its height.
Uh... The work, I believe, of...
uh, "Louis Vau" (Louis le Vau)
- Yes.
- Uh... Mansart... I think...
- Manzard.
- ... and Charles le Brun, I believe.
Yes, that's right.
I could get used to a summer home like this.
- I know you could.
- Me, too,
except, remember: in those days,
they only had baths,
and I'm definitely a shower man.
Where are you two planning on
moving after you get married?
Uh... Malibu.
- Really?
- We're thinking about Malibu, yeah.
I'm pushing for a little
attic in Paris with a skylight.
- La bowhem?
- Yeah,
all that's missing is the tuberculosis.
Exactly. Thank you.
I mean, you know, the problem
is that he's not exactly sure
- he can write a novel.
- Really?
- Well...
- I mean, honey, so far your track record's... you know, and...
well, everyone loves your movies.
- Yeah, well scripts are easier, so...
- Wow.
Why don't you tell them about the lead
character that you're working on right now?
- Yes! - Oh, come on.
- I don't like to discuss my work.
Well, dear, you don't have to tell
them the whole plot, just the character.
- No, no, no.
- Okay.
He works in a nostalgia shop.
- What's a... What's a nostalgia shop?
- Oh, not one of those stores where they sell
Shirley Temple dolls and old radios?
- And I never know who buys that stuff. Who'd want it?
- Exactly.
- I don't know.
- Well, people who live in the past,
people who think that
their lives would be happier
if they lived in an earlier time.
And just which era
would you have preferred
to live in, Miniver Cheevy?
Paris in the '20s, in the rain.
- Wouldn't have been bad.
- And the rain was an acid rain.
Oh, I see! And no global warming,
no TV and suicide bombing,
and nuclear weapons, drug cartels!
Usual menu of clichéd horror stories.
You know, nostalgia is denial.
- Denial of the painful present.
- Oh, whoa!
Gil is a complete romantic.
I mean, he would be
more than happy living in a
complete state of perpetual denial.
- Really?
- And the name for this fallacy
is called "golden-age thinking. "
- Touché.
- Yeah, the erroneous notion that
a different time period is better
than the one one's living in.
It's a flaw in the Romantic
imagination of those people who...
who find it difficult to
cope with the depressive.
- Yes.
- This is the nicest ring we saw.
Diamonds for a wedding band.
That's the way you'd have to go.
And then, everyone will see
it in the back row when
he puts it on my finger.
Oh, Inez. It's gonna be such an event!
- I only wish that...
- I don't want to keep going over it.
It's your choice. What can I say?
Gil is... he's smart,
and he's very successful.
- He talks about giving that all up and moving here!
- Oh, yeah, he TALKS about it.
Well, that frightens me.
This is, of course, Rodin's most famous statue.
A cast of this work was placed next to his tomb.
Rodin wished it to serve as his
headstone and epitaph.
- Is that true?
- It would be in Moudon. He died of the flu,
if I'm not mistaken. In 1917, I believe.
- Very good, sir.
- He's so knowledgeable, isn't he?
Yeah. So much of Rodin's work
was influenced by his wife, Camille.
Yes, she was an influence, though
Camille was not the wife, but his mistress.
- Camille? No.
- Yes.
- Yes. Rose was the wife.
- No, he was never married to Rose.
Yes, he did marry Rose,
- in the last year their lives.
- I think you're mistaken.
Are you arguing with the guide?
- Yes, I am.
- Yeah. No, I'm certain, monsieur.
Yeah, actually, she's right.
I recently read a two-volume
biography on Rodin, and
Rose was definitely the wife.
Camille, the mistress.
- Yeah. You read that? Where did you...
- Yeah, I just read it. I was surprised
because I mistakenly thought,
like you, that it was, yeah,
the other way around.
It's an easy mistake.
So, Dad invited you guys for a wine-tasting.
- Oh, it'll be so French!
- Yeah, yeah.
Paul is an expert on French wine.
- You're joking. Really?
- Yes, of course.
When did you read the biography on Rodin?
Me? Why would I read
a biography on Rodin?
I will always take a California wine, but,
Napa Valley's 6,000 miles away.
John, old boy, how are you, buddy?
Oh, hey! What're you doing here?
Come on. I can't stand that guy.
Um... How 'bout
- we try some more wine?
- Yes! Let's start here.
Now, which would you prefer here?
Well, I think we need
to be scientific and just
start drinking them all again. I don't know.
- Why are your cheeks so red?
- What do you mean?
- They're not red.
- They're bright red.
Oh, maybe it's because of the
pheromones that you're giving off.
These pheromones are driving me mad!
- Stop it! Stop!
- Ahh... Sex and alcohol.
- Yeah.
- It fuels the desire
but kills the performance,
according to the Bard.
Have you tasted the '61?
It is divine!
- Though, Paul picked it out. I didn't...
- What?
- What's happening? What's happening?
- Slightly more tannic than the '59,
and I prefer a smoky feeling
to a fruity feeling.
So, Carol... Carol and I
are gonna go dancing.
We heard of a great place. Interested?
- No... I don't want to be a killjoy,
- Come on!
but I need to get a little fresh air.
Oh, come on! Come on!
Although if you're just gonna sit there and obsess
over where the fire exits are, then...
Hey! If Gil doesn't want to go,
I'll share Paul with you.
I am very democratic,
and Paul is a marvelous dancer.
If it's OK with you,
I think I just want to take a little walk,
go to bed, and then we'll do it another night.
OK. Alright, well I can go, though, right?
- You want to go?
- Well, yeah,
Yeah, I mean, I'm not tired,
and I've been dying to go dancing,
and I'll just meet you back at the hotel.
- I'll take good care of her.
- OK.
I'll get a cab. Taxi!
- OK, but you should take a cab.
- No, I'm not taking a cab. I'm walking.
- No, you'll get lost.
- OK, I'm gonna walk.
Is he a good writer?
I mean, have you read his prose?
- Well, he won't let anybody.
- He won't let?
Oh look, I mean, if he wants, I'd be glad to
look over his novel and critique it for him.
- That would be great!
- Would you?
- You know, I think that's what he needs!
- Yeah?
- Well, it helps.
- To have it read by someone. Yeah!
And you wouldn't pull any punches?
- Well, I certainly won't be letting you know I won't do that.
- No.
I do that about you.
See, but, the problem is,
when it comes to his writing,
he has absolutely no respect
for anybody else's opinion.
Really?
Oh, excuse me! Parlez-vous...
Do you speak English?
- Uh... Hôtel Bristol?
- We don't speak English. Sorry.
Hey! Get in! Come on!
Get in! We're going to leave you!
- What?
- Come on, guy.
- I didn't hear you. What?
- Come on!
Come on, guy!
Get in the car!
Guys, I think you've got me mixed up.
You're making me tired. Come on!
I can't understand you.
I'm a little drunk! I can't...
What is this, an old Peugeot?
I have a friend who collects these in Beverly Hills.
Come on, have a drink. Come on!
- Come on, buddy! Come on!
- OK.
Give me your hand. OK.
Sit down, here.
- Let's go in. Paris, the city of lights.
- Let's go! We're off!
OK, now, where are
you guys taking me?
We're going to party!
Yeah, this isn't quite fair,
'cause I've already had a lot of red wine tonight.
Relax! Have some champagne.
I do like champagne, yeah...
Cheers! Cheers!
- The night is young. Drink up!
- I'm drinking!
- Have a drink!
Yeah, drink up!
[Cole Porter's "Let's Do It, Let's Fall in Love"]
# Let's fall in love #
# In Spain, the best upper-sets do it #
# Lithuanians and Letts do it #
# Let's do it. Let's fall in love. #
# The Dutch in old Amsterdam do it #
# Not to mention the Finns #
# Folks in Siam do it -
think of Siamese twins #
# Some Argentines without means do it #
# People say in Boston even beans do it #
# Let's do it - Let's fall in love #
# Romantic sponges, they say do it #
# Oysters down in Oyster Bay do it #
# Let's do it - Let's fall in love #
- You look lost!
- Oh, yeah!
- You're an American?
- If you count Alabama as America, which I do.
I miss the bathtub gin.
What do you do?
- Me? I'm a writer.
- Who do you write?
- Oh, right now I'm working on a novel.
- Oh, yes?
I'm Zelda, by the way.
Oh, Scott! Scott!
- Yes, what it is, sweetheart?
- Here's a writer, from, um... where?
- California.
- Scott Fitzgerald, and who are you, old sport?
Gil... the...
You have the same names as...
As what?
Scott Fitzgerald and...
Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald. The Fitzgeralds.
Isn't she beautiful?
Yes. Yes! Yeah, that's...
that's a coincidence... like... uh...
You have a glazed look in your eye.
Stunned. Stupefied. Anesthetized. Lobotomized.
I... I... keep looking at the man playing piano, and I
believe it or not, recognize his
face from some old sheet music.
I know I can be one of the great writers
of musical lyrics - not that I can write melodies, and I try,
and then I hear the songs he writes,
and then I realize: I'll never write a great lyric,
- and my talent really lies in drinking.
- Sure does.
Yeah, but, he didn't write the music, did he?
That's not possible...
So... um...
- What kind of books do you write?
- I... I... I'm working on a... um...
Where am I?
Oh, I'm sorry. Don't you know the host?
Some friends have gotten together
a little party for Jean Cocteau.
Hey, lady. What...
Are you kiddding me?
I know what you're thinking.
This is boring. I agree!
I'm ready to move on. Let's do Bricktop's!
- Bricktop's?
- I'm bored! He's bored! We're all bored.
We. Are. All. Bored.
Let's do Bricktop's.
Why don't you tell Cole and Linda
to come with, and... um...
uh... Gil? You coming?
[Cole Porter's "You've Got That Thing"]
# You got that thing - You got that thing #
# The thing that makes birds forget to sing #
# Yes, you've got that thing, that certain thing #
# You've got that charm, that subtle charm #
# that makes young farmers desert the farm #
[Joséphine Baker's "La Conga Blicoti"]
# #
This is one of the finest establishments
in Paris. They do a diamond whiskey sour.
Good evening, everyone!
A small shot of bourbon, please.
Greetings and salutations.
You'll forgive me.
I've been mixing grain and grape.
Now, this a writer. uh... Gil. Yes?
- Gil... Gil Pender.
- Gil Pender.
Hemingway.
Hemingway?
You liked my book?
Liked? I loved!
All your work.
Yes, it was a good book,
because it was an honest book,
and that's what war does to men.
And there's nothing fine and noble
about dying in the mud,
unless you die gracefully,
and then it's not only noble, but brave.
Did you read my story?
What'd you think?
There was some fine writing in it,
but it was unfulfilled.
- I might've known you'd hate it.
- But darling, you're too sensitive.
You liked my story, but he hates me!
Please, old sport,
you make matters extremely difficult.
I'm jumpy. Suddenly I don't like
the atmosphere here any more.
Ah! Where're you going?
To meet some friends on Saint-Germain.
- He's going to Saint-Germain. I'm going with him.
- Zelda, sweetheart...
If you're going to stay here and drink
with him, I'm going with the toreador.
Would you bring her back
at a reasonable time?
- She'll drive you crazy, this woman.
- She's exciting,
and she has talent.
This month it's writing.
Last month it was something else.
You're a writer. You need time to write.
Not all this fooling around.
She's wasting you because she's
really a competitor. Don't you agree?
Me?
Speak up, for Christ's sake! I'm asking if
you think my friend is making a tragic mistake.
Actually, I don't know the Fitzgeralds that well.
You're a writer. You make observations.
You were with them all night!
Could we not discuss my personal life in public?
She's jealous of his gift,
and it's a fine gift. It's rare.
- You like his work? You can speak for it.
- Stop it! Stop it.
You like Mark Twain?
I'm going to find Zelda.
I don't like the thought
of her with that Spaniard.
May I?
Yeah, I'm actually a huge Mark Twain fan.
I think you can even make the case
that all modern American literature
comes from Huckleberry Finn.
- You box?
- No. Not really. No.
What're you writing?
- A novel.
- 'Bout what?
It's about a man who works
in a nostalgia shop.
What the hell is a nostalgia shop?
A place where they sell old things. Memorabilia.
and... Does that sound terrible?
No subject is terrible if the story is true.
If the prose is clean and honest,
and if it affirms grace and co