Downloaded From www.AllSubs.org
Subtitle by
Aldi Arman
I'm already 16 years old...
but I already know how
my life'll look like...
Yesterday, today...
Tomorrow, the day after tomorrow...
Every day, without many changes...
Hey Tanaka!
What's with this melon bread you bought?
Eh?
Don't say 'eh'!!!
The surface is spoilt all over!
This is not how the melon bread should be!
OUCH!
Somehow...
even if I exist or not...
the world is still moving forward.
Hey, koyuki!
How long are you going to let
the Hyoudo band bother you?
Hey!
He's Yukio Tanaka, right?
Why call him Koyuki?
Earlier, there were two
Yukio Tanakas in class.
The smaller one was given the name Koyuki.
It's right.
I'm a boring guy.
I was wondering if I'll always
lead this kind of boring life...
Until I met this one guy...
He looks so scared.
Shaking like a leaf, Man.
You don't hold on tight.
Come on, let's see you jump it.
He ain't taking the risk.
You want us help you jump, huh?
Just f**king jump, Man.
He's f**king ugly!
Do you want us to push you over?
You little freak of nature!
What's that?
Are you some kind of hero?
What are you doing, man?... - Sorry, sorry.
Hey!
Mother fucker man!
Skinny bastard!
Beck!
You think you can get away with
anything, you fucking white trash?
Fuck you!
Apologise to him!
I SAID...
APOLOGISE, Goddamnit!
Are you fine?
It hurts, it hurts!
I got carried away..
This one is Beck!
He is my friend!
I'm Minami Ryusuke.
I'm Yukio Tanaka.
All the people call me Koyuki.
Ah, shit!
Wha... Wait!
Serial Mama
Open/5:30pm-Start/6pm.
Didn't you hear what I said?
Hey Yuji!
Why do we have to die our
hair for the same colour?
That's our band policy.
Our music is not going to get
better with the hair color.
Calm down, calm down!
Calm down, calm down.
That guy's there!
He's got decent technique.
It seems that
guys from the recording company came!
Hey! This guitar! It has holes!
Wha...?
They won't do.
Sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry.
It was a failure!
Us working together.
Ryusuke...
I will create the best band ever!
I will create one too.
Eiji.
This is your punishment!
I'll throw you into the darkest pitch!!
Sorry!
It's your fault!
They found out my meals,
my habit even my address!
Then...
I'll pay you back.
Since when do you have that much?
I'm sorry.
Can't do!
I said calm down!
I'll introduce you to girls!
There are lots to choose from.
Really?
I promise man!
I want a hottie!
Erm...
Beck?
You...
This... what time is... this this one...
What time is your... you know.
Closing time?
Yes, this one!
Japanese language is haaaard!
Obasan, I'm home.
Oh, Beck, welcome home.
I'm living and working here.
I see.
You have lots of CDs here.
Ryusuke-kun.
Did Beck run away again?
Yes.
A regular customer of the
fishing pond - mr. Satou.
Hello.
Greatful Sound.
A festival gathering for all the best bands.
Right, Ryuusuke-kun?
Here, 300 yen.
Good night!
Good Night!
This song... you played it today?
We covered Dying Breed's "Flatliner".
The guy holding a guitar is Dying
Breed's Eddy, my close friend.
Really?
Are you ready asshole?
Telecaster SG.
____caster..Rick 'n Becka ..White Falcon
Rock 'n Roll.
Ryusuke-Kun.
That guitar...
Get the F**K out of here.
Come on Man! I need to see him.
Dying Breed just got a major record deal.
And I can deal with the F***ing top flights,
you know that?
Wait!
Please I gotta leave New York tomorrow.
Hey!... Eddy... Hey, man!
Listen, bro.
You're gonna keep playin' in Japan, right?
Yeah, man.
I know music is gonna keep us together.
Listen, we gotta jam together
again some time, ok?
Doesn't matter if it's a huge festival...
or some tiny fckn club.
Listen... Take this, okay?
Just take it man.
Ray!
Just take it, man.
Take care.
Hey, Eddy!
I'll ______ this
one day.
Aaaaaargh! For God's sake!
Can't you just shut up?!&gt;
I'm trying to read a manga.
Damn it, Maho, I told you
not to come with that act.
Hey! Hey!
My little sis, Maho.
My parents aren't home,
so she's staying here.
Oh!
Oh Yea!
I have to give you
something for saving Beck.
Are you talking about reward?
Oh, don't bother.
C'mon tell me.
Is there anything I can do for you.
Then...
teach me how to play a guitar.
I'll give you this guitar.
If you want me to teach you.
Stop by anytime.
Koyuki-kun!
Hyoudo-Kun asked you to...
buy him a Melon bread.
We told him!
Sensei... Sensei.
Sensei... Sensei!
It's locked.
You! Stop it right now! Hey!
What are you doing!?!!
Stop it, you brat!
It's Dying Breed's "Flatliner".
You chose a cool song.
Who are you?
I'm in Class 1 B... Sakurai Yuji...
I just transferred today.
Sakurai-kun!
It's better if you don't talk to me a lot.
Why?
That guy... is playing guitar at the roof.
That Koyuki is so cocky!
Hey!
So you guys are Hyouda group.
The guys who make school unbearable, huh?
Who the hell are you?
Sakurai-Kun!
I thought I'll give this to you.
Dying breed's live from Germany.
The stairs are barricaded.
The first one was for five days.
Yo!
Can you go drinking today?
So that... erm...
But... we can split the cost...
During the time we didn't see each
other, your Japanese improved greatly.
Well...
It might be sudden, but...
Taira-Kun.
Would you like to be in a band with me?
Ryusuke...
To be honest, Eiji asked me too.
Eh?
The earlier jam with him, you know...
he's improved so much so quickly.
If you want me to play with you...
come when you find an amazing voice.
Let's eat yakiniku (fried meat).
Hey, hey, do you know him?
I ain't gonna tell ya...
You'll know when ya hear him.
Who asked you? You're just a nobody.
You should never get the mic...
Let me tell ya, you gonna get dumped.
Yeah, Yeah, Yeah!
If you're for the MC. Make some noise!
If you're for Chiba. Make some noise!
Chiba!
That's for sure, CHIBA!
DJ Harry, drop it!
Yeah, come on let's do it.
Yeah..
Let's go!
Hurry and just finish
it to the final.
Your rapping is just plain boring.
Shut up and stop your barking...
You'll soon go crying.
Just get it over, I want no more.
I feel sorry for this guy here.
The music, listen to the music...
Or are you deaf and can't hear it?
You've been babbling gibberish..
All this time nothing but gibberish.
You've got no fans, no brothers...
Just go home!
Hey, we've started so
I hafta finish it.
There's still time if
you wanna quit now.
I'll make you regret it all...
I'm gonna beat ya in this show case.
Yeah, yeah, yeah... Look, look...
If you're for Chiba, make some noise!
People for Oz, give him a shout!
The victory goes to Chiba!
Oi, what's wrong, Chiba?
It's not here...
Chiba!
After all, there's only
Taira's bass for our band!
Just tell me the truth.
Is it all about money?...
Aah, that hurts, Man..
Or maybe it's your lucky day.
I don't care whichever way.
You can just do it your way.
I've still got some business to deal with,
so you two can leave first.
What?!
I thought you're going to take
me out to yakiniku!
Get Koyuki to treat you.
Eh?
Hello... Yakiniku?
Hey, Yoshito... What's up!
Right now?
Hey, the girls are really coming?
Wait just a little bit.
The hotties will be here.
Lots to choose from...
Here he comes.
The bassist from earlier...?
Ryusuke, is this that Chiba guy?
Can he really sing?
The other day I met a guy.
He tried to pick me up...
But he's such an asshole, right.
But he drives a BM convertible.
Really? Oh my god, I love that car.
I know, me too...
But you know, he's gross...
Like he twitches his eye when he talks..
Which is so disgusting.
So lame... But there are guys like
that at American schools too, right.
Hey, Guys...
Yoshito!... Hey Maho.
Hey Saori.
You finished shooting?
Hey!
That means toilet, right!
I guess so.
Oh yea, ...
You're not so good with Kanji, right!
Shut the F**K up!... Mind your own business.
Who are you?
What the heck?
What's wrong?
I'm not going home today.
I'll go to Ryusuke's place.
I'm sorry about earlier.
It's ok... It's true that
I'm not good at Japanese.
That's the reason why yesterday...
I got fired from my part time job.
Your Japanese is good enough.
Just Kidding.
I see how it is.
Ryusuke, what's the song?... Evolution.
Let me borrow this mic to tell ya...
There are things out there you've gotta respect.
Now we're here, just try to grab it.
Whatever goal you're aiming for.
Yeah..
Y'all..
Nice to see y'all here, folks..
Hey,
How do you say full moon in Japanese?
"Mangetsu"
Ah, that's it.
I'm walking down this believe
in the hope to find the sun.
And I'm guided by the wind
that blows against my face.
Well, you know I...
"Naked" wasn't it?
Dying Breed's song, right?!
I like it very much so I remembered it.
Was my pronunciation okay?
That guitar...
Let us borrow it for a lil bit.
Did you just...
laugh at me?
Don't play dumb!... You just laughed at me!
I did not.
Saku...
"Ryusuke's Snake Pit"... - Nope!
Minami Ryusuke and Family..
Why's all got your name?!... So lame!!
Shut up... Why don't you
come up with a name then?
Is Beck ok?
But that's a dog.
Now..now..
Lets just use it as a temporary until
we come up with a cooler name.
Okay.
Who are you?
Ah..
Oh, you came!
What's this?
I'm sorry.
It's my fault that this happened.
Get the F**K out of here.
Koyuki...
What's wrong?
Yelling out loud.
Yo!
Did you go to Ryusuke's place?
This can be fixed.
What?
Give it two months, I can have it fixed.
Are you sure?
Why don't I pay for the repair?
Really?
However...
You're a big help!
The Sri Lankan guy who worked here before just quit...
I didn't know what to do.
Doing slave work like this...
no wonder he ran away!
Hey, don't slack!...
Hurry up and finish the job!
We've got a deadline at six o'clock!
The pay is only 500 yen an hour..
This is slavery!
Stop complaining!
Just get the job done!
And then...
Wrong!
How many times do I need to tell you?
Pick on the notes one by one.
Do it again!
Okay.
But why are you wearing swimming gear?
It's hard to tell now, ...
but I was an pre-olympic swimmer when I was young.
Wow, you looked totally different!
When I failed the Olympics selection, ...
I was so depressed... But you know my consolation...?
These guitars!
Amazing!
Now, do it from the beginning!
Okay.
1..2..
Chiba and Taira and Toma and Ryu...
We're BECK.
Evolution!!
Hey!
Koyuki!
Koyuki...
Koyuki.
Hey!
Ryusuke-kun, ... I'm sorry but
working with you isn't fun anymore.
You just don't fit in my scale..
Hey Toma-kun!
Let him go.
Why are you so hasty?
Why did you come here?
I've got the guitar fixed.
Get outta here!
I've got more important stuff to do.
I've got no time to fool
around with you guys!
What the..?!
Shut up, you ass!!
Do you even know how hard
he worked to fix that?
You know..
Yo, Koyuki.
Isn't that the guitar from before?
You got it fixed, huh?
Lend it to me.
No way.
Stop staring, it's annoying!
Teach him a lesson!
Here.
Take this.
Hey!
Hold him.
Stop it there!
Whatcha boys doing?
What's with you?
HEY!
Get away!
He told me everything.
Err...
Ouch!
I know..
1..2..3... YAYYY...!
Doesn't sound like he's just started
playing the guitar a few months ago.
He must be practicing so hard.
Saku..
The drums... Wanna play?
Great..
He's got the feeling for it too.
You want those two with BECK?
Yep.
Just as supporting members first.
Saku is okay...
but Koyuki isn't up at our level yet.
I just wanna... give them a go.
No way!
If we keep going like this, ...
we might have to disband.
Having great musicians doesn't
always guarantee the band's success.
Chemistry is also important.
Is it really okay?...
It's too soon..
You'll make it through.
Let's do it!
After you.
Yeah... After you.
Come on now.
New members of BECK... Koyuki and Saku...
Give 'em your support... Evolution.
Koyuki, stop gazing at the floor!
So terrible!
I missed the last train...
Let me crash here, Koyuki.
Cool!
You made this, Maho?
Yeah, it's my dream.
I wanna be a movie director.
I'm sure you can do it... This is so cool!
I'm off to bed now.
Lend me a T-shirt.
Will I make it?
I feel that I'm stuck.
Ryusuke told me that...
you put too much effort on the action..
But lacking in the feeling, Koyuki.
He said the most important thing is
what you want to express.
You can have that...
It's the pic used by Dying Breed's Eddy.
Eh?
You sure I can have it?
Koyuki, the time will come when you
want to express your feelings too.
But it's been a long time since I saw
Ryusuke having so much fun.
Umm... Eh?!
Koyuki...
Koyuki!
Dying Breed... is coming to Japan!
Yaaaayyyy...
You think Ryusuke-kun will
take us to meet Eddy?
No way!
Dying Breed sold millions
now all over the States.
Anyway, is he really friends with them?
Ouch!
The new song, "Looking Back"
It's not completely done yet.
The music is pretty good, but...
It won't suit Chiba's vocal?
That's it... That's the problem!
But it's my song, so I'll sing it.
It's in English... So I'll do it.
I've passed the English
Proficiency Test level 2.
This song... Can I sing it?
Ah, I mean..
It's about Maho, right?
Jesus Christ...!
Koyuki-kun!
Hey!
But..is it..?
You've got a new vocal, so I'm out?
Idiot!... Our concert
won't be fun without you!
You're our band's greatest front man!
We'd never fire you.
Really?... Really!... That's great!
TV... ON!... Their major debut
has finally been set.
This video clip you're watching
now is their single "Falling"
which was shot at a studio in New York.
... Eiji!
It was directed by the
famous Chris Montgomery.
And produced by the
former producer of Noir.
Rumour has