Cleaned, plenty of OCR issues
corrected and re-synced by Tronar
Hey, buddy.
You don't waste time, do you?
I try not to.
Well, you need help?
Sure.
Would you like to tell us
what the hell that was all about?
I don't like good-byes.
Kind of the point of
a good-bye party, John.
Went to a certain amount
of trouble, you know?
Could've at least stayed
a few minutes, huh?
Eaten some of the food
we so feverishly prepared?
I apologize, Harry.
But why are you moving so quickly?
You only resigned a couple of days ago.
You got the history chair at Stanford.
I wish.
Well, taquitos, chicken wings,
Roastie-Toasties and beer.
If we'd had more time,
we'd have done something
a little more grandiose.
Candlelight dinner at McDonald's.
Strippers.
Taquitos are fine.
A'right.
Art's gonna be along, too.
He's, uh, talking to a student. Pfft.
Is George taking over for you?
- George or Trimbell.
- Has the dean made up his mind?
He hasn't called.
My god!
Wh-What is this?
It looks like a Van Gogh,
But I've never seen it before.
Is that an original, John?
No, it's just a gift someone gave me.
Still, it's a superb copy.
Contemporaneous, I think,
May I take a closer look?
Please, yeah.
Yeah, it's the same
stretcher as Van Gogh used.
Yeah, there's writing
on the back in French.
Oh, "to my friend Jacques Borne."
Wonder who that was?
Someone he knew, I guess.
Brilliant deduction, Sherlock.
Surely you'll have this
looked at, appraised?
Well, maybe sometime,
but I wouldn't really want money for it.
That does it.
Put that stuff in the kitchen.
No, I'm gonna put it
in the bathroom, John.
Gas is off, electricity's on.
Get comfortable while you can.
The furniture's going this afternoon.
It's been years since I sat on a floor.
Heh. I can't remember her name.
Eh, it's good for the back.
Can we do yoga exercises?
Tantric yoga, we can.
So you're leaving
good old "we teach you."
Rather suddenly, you must admit.
Truth time, John.
Is there a problem?
No.
Oh, come on, you know we wanna help.
That's appreciated, but really...
There's no problem.
Well, now I am curious.
Where are you going?
Givin' up tenure...
A decade of professorship,
in line to chain' the department,
and you don't know where you're going?
Call it cabin fever.
After a while, I get itchy feet.
I've done this before.
No, no, no, you're too young
to have done this before.
And he hasn't aged a day in ten years.
Every woman on the faculty
would give anything to have that secret.
Is that what they're after, Edith?
Oh, stop, Harry.
Wow, can you pull this?
What the hell?
What do you hunt?
Deer, mostly.
Around big bear.
With a bow and arrow?
Most people can't bag a deer
with a rifle and a telescopic sight.
Though, good eatin'.
The best wild game.
Lives naturally, eats naturally.
Well, it's beautiful.
Art.
Ah.
So, can I get an "a" for awesome?
Oh, my gosh.
That was fun.
Hey, John.
You know Linda.
You had her last semester.
Hi. Hey.
She's one of my victims now.
I'm taking her home.
She wanted to come by
and say hello good-bye.
Is Art as tough as I hear?
Oh, archaeology's tough.
Dr. Jenkins is a fine teacher.
Oh, that's very politic.
It's very true. Uh-huh.
Something for you to
read on the road, pal.
"Shadows of the cave:
parallels to early man."
M. Jenkins.
Publish or perish.
I'd rather read
than write another one.
Thank you.
Hi.
Oh, everybody, this is Linda.
Linda, this is everybody.
Linda. Hi.
So.
Where you going, John,
like we give a damn?
We've already covered that.
John's got itchy feet.
There are over-the-counter
remedies for that, John.
So there is a problem.
No.
I just like to move on now and then.
It's a personal thing.
Well, not to pry.
I'm sorry I don't
have more to offer you.
Got conversation, some
seats for your behinds,
And, uh...
Is he ducking out on us again?
...I do have this.
Oh ho ho! Johnny Walker green!
Didn't even
know they made it in green.
What do they pay you?
Nothing is too good for my friends.
But I'm sorry,
we are down to plastic cups now.
That's a sacrilege I'll tolerate.
I will do the honors.
Oh, come to papa.
Ooh! Here, cups, cups.
There we go.
Step on in here.
There ya go...
One for the birthday boy...
Excuse me. Art?
No, not for me.
Oh, no, I don't drink.
We're not
gonna card you, darling.
All right, here, join
the circle at least.
Well, to long life and good fortune.
To our esteemed friend
and colleague, John Oldman.
May he find undeserved bliss
wherever he goes.
Hear, hear.
Skol. Na zdorovye.
One off the top, John.
Mm! Oh, that's good.
Excuse me.
John, we're all sorry to see you go.
Truly.
Okay. Now we're done with that,
what do we do for the
rest of the afternoon?
Anyone got a good topic?
Like this, maybe? Heh.
What is that?
It's a burin off a parrot beak.
Inclined chisel point...
Probably early Magdalenian.
- May I see that?
- Sure.
Yes indeed, that's what it is.
What's a burin?
A burin is a flint tool
for grooving wood and
bone, antlers especially,
to make spear and harpoon points.
Magdalenians weren't
noted for flint work,
so this is a very nice specimen.
Okay, what's a Magdalenian?
A later Cro-Magnon,
without gettin' technical.
It's the final culture
of the upper Paleolithic.
If stones could speak, eh, Art?
So where'd you get that, John?
Believe it or not, from a thrift shop.
A quarter.
You lucky dog!
I gotta go digging
for this kind of stuff.
Can I, uh?
Yeah.
Huh.
Maybe...
I'm glad you did this.
Did what? You mean come over?
Maybe?
Definitely.
Gee, thanks.
Well, so are we.
So are we.
We couldn't let you just run off.
Thanks.
John, what is up, huh?
Are you on America's most wanted?
We won't turn you in.
Yeah, come on, out with it.
You're among friends.
Snoopy friends.
Forget it.
You are creating the mystery here.
Obviously, you have something
you'd like to say. Say it!
Well, maybe I...
Ten, nine, eight, seven...
Harry, stop.
There is something I'm
tempted to tell you, I think.
I've never done this before,
and I wonder how it'll pan out.
I wonder if I could ask
you a silly question.
John, we're teachers.
We answer silly questions all the time.
Hey!
What if a man from the upper Paleolithic
survived until the present day?
What do you mean, survived?
Never died?
Yes. What would he be like?
Well, I know some guys.
You ever been to the Ozarks?
It's an interesting idea.
What, are you working on
a science fiction story?
Say I am. What would he be like?
Pretty tired.
Well, seriously,
As Art's book title suggests,
he might be like any of us.
Dan. A caveman?
Well, there's no anatomical difference
between, say, a Cro-Magnon and us.
Except that as a rule,
we've grown taller.
What's the selective
advantage of height?
Better to see predators
in tall grass, my dear.
Actually, tall and skinny
radiates heat more
effectively in warmer climates.
And as for Neanderthals,
I mean, we've all seen apish people.
That strain's still with us.
But he'd be a caveman.
No, he wouldn't.
John's hypothetical man
would have lived
through 140 centuries...
Yeah, roughly.
...and changed with every one of them.
I mean, assuming normal intelligence.
Well, we think men of
the upper Paleolithic
were as intelligent as we are.
They just didn't know as much.
John's man would have
learned as the race learned.
In fact, if he had an inquiring mind,
his knowledge might be astonishing.
If you do write that,
let me have a look at it.
I'm sure you'll make some
anthropological boners.
It's a deal.
What would keep him alive?
What does the biologist say?
Cigarettes.
And ice cream.
All right, all right, I'll play.
All right, um, in science fiction terms,
I would say...
Perfect regeneration
of the body's cells,
especially in the vital organs.
Actually, the human
body appears designed
to live about 190 years.
Most of us just die of slow poisoning.
Maybe he did something right,
something everybody else
in history had done wrong.
What, like eat the food,
drink the water, and breathe the air?
Prior to modern times,
those were pristine.
We've extended our lifespan
in a world that's, uh...
not fit to live in.
You know, it could happen.
The pancreas turns over
cells every 24 hours,
the stomach lining in three days,
the entire body in seven years,
but the process falters.
Waste accumulates, eventually
proves fatal to function.
Now if a quirk in his immune system
led to perfect detox,
perfect renewal, then yeah.
He could duck decay.
Mm, that's a secret
we'd all love to have.
Would you really want to do that?
Live 14,000 years?
Well, if I could stay
healthy and I didn't age,
I mean, why not?
Yeah. What a chance to learn.
Is anyone hungry?
You know, the more I think
about it, yeah, it's possible.
Anything is possible, right?
After all, one century's magic,
another century's science.
They thought Columbus
was a nut job, right?
Pasteur, Copernicus?
Aristarchus long before that.
Right.
I had a chance to sail with Columbus,
Only I'm not the adventurous type.
I was pretty sure the Earth was round,
but at that point, I still thought
he might fall off an edge someplace...
Look around, John.
We just did.
I suppose there's a
joke in there somewhere,
but I don't get it.
There's nothing to get.
What are we talking about?
We were just talking about a caveman
who survives until the present time.
As you said, what a chance to learn,
once I learned to learn.
Did you start the whiskey
before we got here?
Pretend it's science fiction.
Figure it out.
Okay, a...
very old Cro-Magnon
living until the present.
Oh!
What?
John just confided that
he's 14,000 years old.
Oh, John, you don't look a day over 900.
Okay, okay.
All right, Spock, I'll
play your little game.
What do you want? What's the punch line?
Every ten years or so, when people start
to notice I don't age, I move on.
That's very good,
that's very quick, John.
I wanna read that
story when you're done.
You want more?
By all means. This is great.
All right, now...
So you think that you are a...
A, uh, Cro-Magnon.
Well, I didn't learn it in school.
That's my best guess,
based on archaeological data,
maps, anthropological research.
Since Mesopotamia,
I've got the last...
4,000 years straight.
You're ahead of most
people, so please, go on.
Well, you know the background stuff,
so I'll make it brief.
In what I call my first lifetime,
I aged to about 35...
what you see.
I ended up leading my group.
They saw me as magical.
I didn't even have to fight for it.
Then fear came, and they chased me away.
They thought that I was
stealing their lives away to stay young.
The prehistoric origin
of the vampire myth.
That is good!
First thousand years,
I didn't know up from sideways.
How do you know the
first thousand years?
An informed guess, based on what
I've learned in my memories.
Most people can scarcely
remember their childhood,
but you have memories of that time?
Like yours, selective.
You know, the high points,
the low points, traumas.
They stick in the mind forever.
Put down at 3 or 35,
you still feel a twinge.
Go on.
I kept getting chased
because I wouldn't die,
so I got the hang of
joining new groups I found.
I also got the idea of
periodically moving on.
We were semi-nomadic, of course,
following the weather
and the game we hunted.
The first 2,000 years were cold.
We learned it was warmer
at lower elevations.
Late glacial period, I assume.
What was the terrain like?
Mountainous.
Vast plains to the west.
West - something you learned in school.
Towards the setting sun.
I suspect I saw the British isles
from what is now the French coast.
Huge mountains...
on the other side of
an enormous deep valley
that was shadowed by the setting sun.
This is before they were separated
from the continent by rising
seas, as glaciers melted.
That happened?
Yes, the end of the Pleistocene.
So far, what he says fits.
Oh, yeah, into any textbook.
And that's where I found it.
How can I have knowledgeable recall
if I didn't have knowledge?
It's all retrospective.
All I can do is
integrate my recollections
with modern findings.
Caveman, you gonna hit me
over the head with a club
and drag me into the bedroom?
You'd be more fun conscious.
Oh, John.
Let me get this straight.
We're not talking about reincarnation.
You're not saying that you remember
whatever the hell it would be,
200 separate lifetimes, dying
and being born again and yada yada?
One lifetime.
Some lifetime.
Wow.
Maybe there is something
to this reincarnation thing.
You're supposed to come back
again and again, learn and learn,
and somehow, John, you just managed
to bypass all the other bodies.
Well, what's the point?
What about oceans?
Didn't see them till much later.
So how would you know
an ocean from a lake?
Big waves - something else.
I can only surmise in retrospect.
Were you curious about
where it all came from?
We would look up at the sky and wonder.
"There's gotta be
some big guys up there.
What else made all this down here?"
At first I thought
there was something wrong with me -
maybe I was a bad guy for not dying.
Then I began to wonder if I was cursed
or perhaps blessed.
Then I thought maybe I had a mission.
Do you still think you do?
God works in mysterious ways.
I think I just happened.
Wow.
Hello?
Yes, Ellie?
What's wrong?
Sandy?
Coming.
Yeah?
Do we have Ellie's midterm here?
Yeah, sorry.
I picked it up with the periodicals.
Got it.
No, you're worried about your parents?
Don't... don't worry.
You passed, C+.
Take care of yourself.
Good kid.
What does pre-med need with history?
Got it.
Thank you.
Sorry, guys.
John, please continue.
Come on, I thought we
were done with that.
No! Let's go on with it.
It's interesting.
Besides, I think he's making
a certain amount of sense.
Like Hegel.
Logic from absurd premises.
That Van Gogh?
He gave it to me.
I was, uh, Jacques Bourne at the time,
A pig farmer.
A pig farmer?
I like to work with my hands.
He would come out to the place, paint.
We talked about capturing nature in art.
Turner, Cezanne, Pissarro.
Oh, the Nolde landscapes.
Not in Van Gogh's time.
He would have loved them, though.
Yes.
Well, I don't understand
why you can't remember
where you're from.
00:18:53,998